<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funerall sermon that was prepared to haue b[i]ne preached, by Robert King doctour in diuinit[y] for a cert[e]in honourable lady then almoste deade, but afterward recouered, to who[m] in writing this sermon was giuen, that she being[e] alyue, mighte read[e] what should haue b[i]ne preached at her death: howbeit now[e] God hath done his will vpon her and hath called her (I doubt not) to himselfe. But now it is here set forth[e] as it was deliuered to her then be[i]nge al[i]ue</title>
            <author>King, Robert, d. 1557.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1552</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14992.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900279</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1966:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funerall sermon that was prepared to haue b[i]ne preached, by Robert King doctour in diuinit[y] for a cert[e]in honourable lady then almoste deade, but afterward recouered, to who[m] in writing this sermon was giuen, that she being[e] alyue, mighte read[e] what should haue b[i]ne preached at her death: howbeit now[e] God hath done his will vpon her and hath called her (I doubt not) to himselfe. But now it is here set forth[e] as it was deliuered to her then be[i]nge al[i]ue</title>
                  <author>King, Robert, d. 1557.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[110] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Richard Grafton],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1552.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G (-G8, blank?)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Exeter College Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150659:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A funerall ſermon that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne preached, by Robert king doctour in diuinit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for a cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in honourable Lady then almoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward recouered, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Sermon was g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen, that ſhe be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue, might<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what ſhould haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preached at her death: howbeit now<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God hath done his will vpon her and hath called her (I doubt not) to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But now it is here ſet f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as it was deliuered to her then be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nge al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue. 1552.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:150659:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150659:2"/>
            <head>The preface or Epiſtle to this Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I looked amonge pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of myne olde ſtudied notes and ſermones (moſt gentle Lady) by chaunce I founde a draught of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that was prepared, to haue bene preched at your buryall. This was when your Ladiſhippe was ſo dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſicke at Chelſie. Then was I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of one of your cheefe officers to prepare a ſermon for your burial, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was thought to come ſhortly, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thynge made a greate many of vs your ſeruauntes ful heuy. But in ſuch a caſe no thought wylle helpe. And I knowyng that ſuche a thyng wolde be loked for at my hande, with an heuie harte I prepared this preſent ſermon (althoughe it be nowe a litle more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated) to be in a redines, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of all them, that ſhould haue bene preſent at your buriyng, to lerne them<pb facs="tcp:150659:3"/>howe they ſhould preare themſelues to die. And now (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be vnto god,) whiche dothe ordre all thynges to the beſt, ſo that, that ſermon whiche was prepared for to haue edified &amp; ben pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to other then, mai be profitable to teache your good Ladiſhippe now, in readyng of theſame, bothe to lyue and to die. It ſhall not be onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to you, but alſo to as many as ſhal either reade it or heare it. I praye you good madame remember this one thynge well, althoughe death dyd but dalye with you then, to put you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce that ye be mortall, ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he will come again a nother tyme, and execute his office vpon you euen in earneſt. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſhalbe, ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell, therfore be alwaies in a redy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for as our Sauiour Chriſte ſaith: Ye know neither the daye nor yet the houre. &amp;c. watche therfore and be all times in a redines. Heare I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to note &amp; beare in mynde, that the exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I purpoſed to haue
<pb facs="tcp:150659:3"/>ſpoken to them that ſhould haue bene hearers alyue at your buryng: Nowe heare I ſpeake theſame (by my penne) to you, ye thankes be vnto god beyng aliue, and may by readyng of theſame knowe what ſhould haue bene ſpoken vnto other. And thoughe it maye bee ſumwhat merueiled at, why that I name you ſo often in this my preface, as though al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole exhortacion wer made onely vnto you. The cauſe why I name you ſo often is ths. In your name or your perſon, I admony ſhe as mani as ſhal either heare or reade this poore exhortacion. Remember good Lady, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, yea euen in your moſt proſperite, what ye ſhalbe in aduerſite Remember in your pleaſaunte lyfe, what ye ſhalbe after your dolorous death. It is not for naught, that the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>Memorare nouiſſima tua, &amp; in eternum non peccabis,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (ſaith he) thy laſt end, (erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and often, &amp; I warraunt the) thou ſhalt neuer ſynne, wyllyngly. And ſo <pb facs="tcp:150659:4"/>conſequently, thou ſhal neuer be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. A worthy bill of remembraunce, often to be loked vpon: Yet moreouer I truſte (good Lady) that theſe doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whiche are neceſſary for al maner of perſones, ſhalbe alſo your inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for there is no perſon ſo perfecte, no nor yet ſo well lerned, but he or ſhe, may be better, bothe in learnynge and liuynge. There is no perſone ſo wittie or wiſe, but by hearyng of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctrine, he or ſhe maye bee made wiſer: accordyng to the ſaiyng of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon in the firſte chapiter of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes. <hi>Audiens ſapiens, ſapientior eris:</hi> The wiſe hearyng, ſhalbe wiſer. Moreouer, that that I write to your good Ladiſhippe nowe, for your good inſtruction, both to liue and to die by, I doubt not but that ye will imparte and communicate the ſame, with your moſte dearly beloued huſbande, my eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecyall good Lord and maiſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which I am ſure wilbe as gladde to heare it, as your Ladiſhippe wyll bee to reade<pb facs="tcp:150659:4"/>it, for he that ſo often vouchedſaulf to heare me preche, wyll nowe I doubte not heare that that I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for I haue euen now with as good an harte written vnto you, as I was wonte to preache before you. And am now as ready as euer I was to do you ſeruice if time and place would ſuffer. But bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which wilnot be now brought to paſſe, a nother time God wylling ſhall wel come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>¶ I woulde wyſhe nowe that this poore exhortacion ware euen as a glaſſe afore your eyes, and as a bill of remembraunce afore your myndes, bothe to thynke how that ye do lyue, and alſo howe that ye ſhould liue, and conſider erneſtly, what ye do, &amp; what ye be commaunded of God to do, Let the holy ſcripture in all theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, be your rule. Alſo conſider, what ye be now by the goodnes of god, and what ye ſhalbe hereafter by the courſe of nature. What ye haue receiued at goddes handes, &amp; how that ye vſe ſuch<pb facs="tcp:150659:5"/>thynges ſo receiued, ye muſte remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo, that he that dothe receiue muche at his lordes handes, muſte ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a compte of muche. And he that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a good accompte of many thinges wel beſtowed accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to his maiſters minde, ſhall haue greate thankes, and be ſette ouer muche more after then he was before Mathew .xxv. I truſt that both my good lorde and you alſo, will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be content wyth my writyng now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, both boldely, plainly and truly, as well as ye haue bene content in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt to heare me preche before you bothe boldly, truely and plainely. And not onely contented to heare me ſo preache, but alſo, to defende me ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng. Yet moreouer I truſte, that your wiſedome, knowynge my rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ruſticalnes and plaines, will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider the thynges that be here writen, with the meanyng of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then to loke for ſuche thynges as ye knowe, by your olde experience not to be in him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Colors of rethori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cke,<pb facs="tcp:150659:5"/>Eloquence of ſpeche, Craftie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiaunce of matter, Fine termes, pure Engliſhe, and ortographically writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, &amp; ſuche like, wher as the prouerbe ſaithe, where nothynge is, the kyng loſeth his right. So your good Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe muſte be fayne to be contented with ſuche as heare is, ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he that ſent your Ladiſhip this, would with al his harte, haue ſent you a better made thyng, if there had bene any better in his ſtore houſe, Therfore I beſech you my good Lady, take it in good worth nowe, and when god geueth better, ye ſhal haue better, Laſt of al I would be gladde, that you of your accuſtomed goodnes, would voucheſaulfe to take the payne to loke ouer this poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, erneſtly &amp; often. Yet becauſe it is ſumwhat long: I haue diuided it in to v. partes, that ye may reade ouer one parte at once, and ſo at length all. I woulde deſire you at the leſte wiſe to loke ouer, the firſt and the ſconde par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and that as I haue ſaied, bothe<pb facs="tcp:150659:6"/>erneſtly and often. For although it be, very good &amp; expedient to know diuerſe playſters and medicynes for dyuers ſores and ſickeneſſes, yet we muſte vſe thoſe moſte, that we knowe will helpe ouer ſores and diſeaſes beſt.</p>
            <p>¶ Nowe when I had made an ende of this poore exhortacion, it came into my mynde, that a newe yere was at hand, a tyme wherin, both men &amp; women, be wonte to gratifie there fryndes with ſuche giftes, as are bothe pleaſaunte and profitable in this lyfe. But I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to gratifie you my eſpecial good Lady, and maiſtres, with ſuche a Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel or gyfte, out of the treaſure houſe of god, that if ye kepe it wel and vſe it wel, it ſhalbe vnto you, both pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, profitable &amp; permanent, not onely for this preſent lyfe, but alſo for the life that is to come, &amp; ſhall dure for euer. Other imagyne in this mery tyme of Chriſtmas, to make ther frindes mery &amp; gladde in body. But I go about to make my fryndes (amonge whom my<pb facs="tcp:150659:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lorde and you bee the chefe and all) mery and gladde in couſcience, that is, when ye ſo lyue as though ye ware euer redie to die, and gladde to be in heauen, with your Lorde Chriſte, who euer preſerue my good Lord and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, your good Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe and al yours bothe in honour heare, and in glory ther. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your ſeruaunte Roberte k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vncha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngeable pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> facion.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:150659:7"/>
            <head>A preface into the Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am comen hether this daye (Chriſten audy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) to preche at the buriall of this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbe Lady, my good Lady and Maiſtres. That that ſhalbe preached heare at this time, ſhal be to her nothing profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: for lernynge tyme, wyth her is paſt, but this ſermon may be vnto you al, that ſhalbe the hearers of theſame, if ye imprinte it wel in your mynd, and bere it wel away profitable. It may be (I ſai) profitable to you al, of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſtate, condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or degree, ye be of.</p>
            <p>¶ I haue choſen he parable, that our Sauiour Chriſte ſpeketh of in the xvj. chapiter of ſainte Luke, to treate of this day: out of the which parable, euery man mai learne, that marketh it wel, bothe how he dothe and alſo how he ſhoulde liue. And howe that if he lyue heare well, he ſhall euer after lyue well in ioye and pleaſure. The contrary, if that he lyue not heare<pb facs="tcp:150659:7"/>well, he ſhall no lyue hereafter, that is, he ſhall be damned and ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall payne in hell. That we all may heare the doctrine of this parable preched ſo, that it may be to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of goddes glory and to the profite and vtilitie of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you for to pray. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150659:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Sermon.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was a certayne riche man, which was clothed in purple and fyne white, and fared delyciouſly euery daye &amp;c. Our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte (honourable audyence) in the beginnyng of this .xvj. chapter of the holy Euangeliſte ſaynte Luke, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouned &amp; ſetfurthe a parable of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn wicked and craftie Stewarde, whom he lawded, becauſe he ordered the matter ſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his maiſters fermers and tenauntes, that he ſhould neuer wante whiles they had. This mans wiſedome, was lauded of our ſauiour Chriſt, not becauſe it was wicked, but becauſe he made prouiſyon, that is to ſay fryndes, here in this preſent world, for the tyme that was to come. And ſo in this parable of this wicked Stuard he techeth vs all to make vs frendes whiles that we be here in this preſent worlde, that we lacke not in the world that is to come. Theſe be our ſaluiour Chriſtes woordes, and the hole pitthe <pb facs="tcp:150659:8"/>openyng of this afore named parable. And I ſaie (ſaith he) make you frendes of the vnrighteous and wicked Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that when ye ſhall haue nede, they maie receiue you into euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng habitacions. There ſhall a greate chaunge come at that daie, where the pacient and the thankefull poore beggers, ſhalbe very ryche. And the vnmercifull and vnthankefull riche ſhalbe very beggers and poore. This is the riches that the pacient &amp; thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poore beggers ſhall receiue: euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng, (that is to ſaie) felicytie and glory with god in heauen. And this is the pouertie and beggery that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull and vnthankefull riche men ſhall receiue with the deuell in hell, that is to ſaie euerlaſtynge payne and miſery. This doctryne is bothe liuely and truly ſetfurth in this parable of <hi>Diues and Lazarus,</hi> that is to ſaie in the parable of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> richeman &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore begger Lazarus. Althing heare in this parable, is ſetfurth ſo liuely &amp; plainly, that a man marking it thoroughly and<pb facs="tcp:150659:9"/>depely, with all the circumſtaunces of theſame, ſhal rather thynke, that he ſeeth althynges done before his eyes, as it ware played in a playe, and euery perſone ſene, then to haue redde it or to haue harde it preached. Nowe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this parable of this richeman &amp; of this begger, ware a thyng that was done in dede, or rather a thynge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by our ſauiour Chriſt to teche with all ſuche thynges as be heare taught: it maketh no matter for vs to know. Let vs conſider, vs (I ſay) whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che either bee, or oughte to bee very Chriſtians, lette vs marke well, and depely conſider, what thynges bee taught in this parable for our inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and lerninges, and let vs beleue the doctrines of theſame to bee moſte true. And that the ſelfſame thynges here taught in the parable, ſhall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce vnto vs, if we do as they dyd. Let vs therfore haue contynually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes I ſay of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: theſe .ij. perſones in this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable or example: ſetfurth (and by our<pb facs="tcp:150659:9"/>ſauiour Chriſte to learne vs by. This parable is very neceſſary and alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable &amp; worthy to be had in memory of all men, whether they be riche or poore, for there is no perſone of what ſoeuer degree or ſtate, he or ſhe be, but may learne by this parable. The riche may learne &amp; beware by it. The poore man maye learne and take greate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it. I would wyſhe this ſtorie or parable to be painted or graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in euery mannes houſe; but rather imprinted in euery mannes conſcience &amp; memory.</p>
               <p>Nowe let vs come vnto the parable, &amp; therein marke, both notable wordes and ſentences. There was a certeyne Riche man, whiche was clothed in purple and fyne whyte, and fared de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly euery daie. The holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth .ij. maner or ſortes of riche men. The one ſorte are ſuche as are riche in God. The other ſorte that are riche to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. They are riche in God, that knowe that all riches are geuen and come of god, and muſte be ſpent accordynge to the will and<pb facs="tcp:150659:10"/>pleaſure of God. They knowe what Dauid in his xxiij. Pſalme dothe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and ſaie, not onely with mouthe but alſo wyth harte: in theſe wordes.
<hi>Domini eſt terra, &amp; plenitudo eius:</hi> The earthe is the Lordes and all the plentuouſnes that is in it Ergo ſuche goodes as we haue and poſſeſſe, be not ours, but the lordes. We haue but the vſe of them, and ſhall make a ſtrait compt for them how that we vſe them ether to our own, or to the lordes vſe, to our owne profite and pleaſure, or to the lordes profite or pleaſure. If that we erneſtly, woulde weye theſe wordes and erneſtly beleue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be true (as they be moſte erneſtly to be waied, and alſo moſt erneſtly to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued,) I ſuppoſe we ſhould not be ſo vnthankeful in receiuing, ſo vnwares either in kepyng or ſpending, contrary to the wil and pleaſur of the owner of them as we now are. Then ſhould we receiue of the handes of our Lorde a great ſumme or porcion of his goodes, loke to make of theſame Lord, a great<pb facs="tcp:150659:10"/>and a perfete compte for thoſe goodes receyued. I pray you, doe no greate riche men of the woorlde, looke for a compte of them to whom they commit ther ſubſtaunce or goodes. Is it not right and reaſon that the tenauntes, knowe their lande lordes, and ones in the yere to paye their rentes, and knowleage their dueties. Seyng that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue aught, do loke to haue their deuties paied and done vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordyng to couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, why ſhould not al men both highe and lowe noble and vnnoble, looke to do their duties to their lorde god? Let them conſider they haue receiued that that thei haue they be none owners, they be but ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes and diſpoſers of their Lordes goodes. God geue grace to all ſuche ſeruauntes, to receiue ſuche thynges, as they receiue truly, and to ſpende and beſtowe their goodes truly, that in tyme to come, they may make ſuche a compte, as ſhalbe thankfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and they to be rewarded abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly. Of ſuche a ſeruaunte Dauid<pb facs="tcp:150659:11"/>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tethe in the .Cxij. Pſalme thus ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng:
<hi>Opes &amp; diuitiae in domo eius &amp; iuſticia eius manet ineternum.</hi> Abundance and greate riches are in his houſe, and his rightuouſnes and vprighte dealynge remayneth for euer. He ſaith not, Robberyes, euell gotten goodes and vſury are in his houſe: for then Dauid wold haue ſaid that his vnrightuouſnes and ſubtile dealyng had remained in his houſe for euer. Here lette vs weye and depely conſider, the great gyfte of god wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by theſe .ij. thynges may be ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one houſe, that is to ſaye, rghtuouſnes and Riches. When the good man of the houſe is bothe Riche and rightuous, howe muche is that man bounde to God. For ſeldome be theſe .ij. giſtes lodged in one houſe. And yet it is not vnpoſſible to God although it be vnpoſſible to man. We reade in holy ſcripture of many (by the goodnes of god) that ware bothe riche and rightuous. As Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, Ioſeph, Samuel, Iob; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,
<pb facs="tcp:150659:11"/>&amp;c. Theſe men ware more then men, for they wer good men, that both feared god &amp; loued god, &amp; that by hys grace and goodnes: whiche was not receiued of them in vaine, they vſed al their goodes to godes will &amp; pleaſure. And ſo doe all good men that are riche in god. Richeſſe and pouertie of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, be thynges indifferente neither good nor badde, but the vſe of them maketh all. God is not pleaſed by and by, becauſe that a man is poore, for there be many poore that be alſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and none more wicked then they. Nether is god diſpleaſed, becauſe a man is riche, for ther haue bene, and I doute not but ther be, many riche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe riche &amp; good alſo, that pleaſen god right well. For riches be meanes and inſtrumentes, wherby God maie be pleaſed, if thei that poſſeſſe them, be bothe riche and rightuous. Then doe they vſe there richeſſe to goddes ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſure and poore mens profettes. And they beynge ſuche riche men, there ſpryngethe out of them as it ware .ij.<pb facs="tcp:150659:12"/>founteynes, one is: they will do good, And another y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are able to do that good that they wil. Here ye ſee, that the riche man may do one thynge, that the poore cannot do, That is, he hath wherwith to do that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will do, &amp; ſo hath not the poore man, yet for al that the poore man is neuer the more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightuous becauſe he hath not to do with all, but it is ſufficyente for hym to whom god geueth nomore, to haue a good will and a mercifull harte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes all them that haue nede. And lette hym deale hys almoſe with hys tongue, in comfortynge, counſeilynge and exhorting other to pacience and to al other goodnes. But although the rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be bound to do al theſe, yet he muſt helpe the neadie to, with his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce accordynge to his abilytie and their neceſſitie, or els he is not that man, that is afore ſpoken of, that is bothe riche and rightuous. I pray god make all them that haue riches of god geuen vnto them, or rather lent vnto them, to be of this ſort, that is bothe<pb facs="tcp:150659:12"/>riche and rightuous, and to conſider deaply the will of god, and to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber charitably, the nede of their poore neighbours. It foloweth alſo in the afore reherſed texte <hi>&amp; Iuſticia eius manet ineternum.</hi> His rightuouſnes dothe remaine for euer. Aboundaunce and richeſſe remainethe not for euer, but the righte vſyng of them and the vpright dealing with them remaineth for euer. Some men perchaunce will ſay, ſir ye ſay wel, that I muſte helpe and releue my neighboures nedes and neceſſities. But I pray you tel me? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not my gooddes mine owne gooddes, and maie not I beſtowe them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to mine owne mind? This obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is anſwered to partely before, but heareafter it ſhalbe anſwered fully, that neither the gooddes that thou haſte in thy poſſeſſyon, are thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but goddes gooddes, and are not geuen the to be beſtowed at thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but at goddes pleaſure. Heare and marke it wel in this matter, what the holy man Dauid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ciiij. pſalme
<pb facs="tcp:150659:13"/>ſaith. <hi>Impleta eſt terra facultatibus, tuis.</hi> The earthe O lorde (ſaith he) is repleniſhed with thy goodes and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Then if we beleue the ſaiyng of this holy man Dauid, as we muſte nedes and are bounde to do, becauſe it is autenticke ſcripture. We ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that al the goodes and ſubſtance that is on the earth, is the Lordes and not ours, and that we be but balliefes and Stuardes of theſame, to beſtowe them after his wyll and not after our owne wyll, &amp; that on payne of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Wylt thou knowe what is thine owne proper good, among al the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the earth, conſider well what thou broughteſt in with the in to this world, that is to ſay, nothyng, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that nothynge maiſte thou beſtowe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to thyne owne will, for all other thynges are to be beſtowed accordyng to the Lordes will, that is the owner of them. Perchaunce a man will ſaie, although I brought nothing into this world with me, yet ther be many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that I my ſelf with my witte and<pb facs="tcp:150659:13"/>wiſedome, with my diligence and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cye haue gotten, may I not beſtowe thoſe goodes at myne owne will and pleaſure? I pray the tell me, who gaue the that witte and wiſedom, that with thy diligence &amp; policie, thou haſte got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe (as thou accompteſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) thyne owne goodes? Did not god geue the al that thou haſte, witte, reaſon, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge, knowlege, and whatſoeuer thou haſte els, to ſerue hym with all. Art not thou his bounde ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with all that thou haſte, and arte bounde to ſerue him to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermoſt of thi powre? May a ſeruaunt that is ſure bounde to his maiſter, make himſelfe free, and to do what hym lyſte, when he wyll? Standeth he not bound to his maiſter to do hym ſeruice, to the vttermoſte of his powre, with all his witte, with all his reaſon, with all his vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge and knowlege, &amp; with all that is poſſible for him to do, and thus muſte he continue vntill the tyme his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt be out? Are not all manner of perſons with all there qualities, both<pb facs="tcp:150659:14"/>inwarde and outwarde, bothe greate and ſmall, high &amp; lowe, men &amp; women, from the higheſt ſorte to the loweſt, bounde to ſerue God with all there goodes and ſubſtance, and with al that thei haue or be beſide. Who hath made any man free from this ſeruice? Not god: for he ſaith in the .xij. chapiter of Exodus <hi>Ego ſum dominus deus tuus</hi> I am (ſaithe he) the Lorde thy God. This ſaiynge is ſpoken to euery man and woman of whatſoeuer ſtate they be, here is none excepted. If god be the Lorde of vs all: be not we then all hys ſeruauntes, wyth all our qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. Who hath made vs free? Not god, for he wil neuer make vs free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys ſeruice, ſo longe as we be in this body, Can we make ourſelues free? That cannot a ſeruaunte do duryng his couenant. Our couenant is made, it cannot be broken durynge this lyfe. Therefore we with all that we haue be goddes bound ſeruauntes, and are bounde to ſerue hym faithfully and truly, and that to our ende euen on<pb facs="tcp:150659:14"/>panye of Damnacion. Nowe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ye that wylbe ryche and rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſee that ye get youre gooddes accordyng to the wyll of God godly, kepe them godly &amp; ſpende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> godly, be mercyfull to the poore and nedye, be not hyghe mynded and haultie ouer other that be poore, Truſte not in vncerteyn riches, but in the liuynge God, be riche in good workes: for all theſe leſſons dothe the holy Apoſtle Paule teche vs, in his firſte Epiſtle to Timothe .vj. Suche a nother good leſſon dothe Dauid teche vs in the lxxxj. Pſalme ſaiynge: <hi>Si diuitiae af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluunt, nolite cor apponere.</hi> If riches (ſaithe he) flowe or be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dante, ſette not your harte on them, Make not your good, your God. Serue you your God, and lette your good ſerue you.</p>
               <p>Nowe heare ye haue heard the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of thoſe riche men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are bothe Ryche and Rightuous, and they that are ſuche are alſo Ryche in God. I beſeche God of his infinite goodnes, to<pb facs="tcp:150659:15"/>geue vs all grace to learne to be riche in this wiſe, that is in God, &amp; to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe the ſame in our liuynge, whiche ſhalbe if that we be ryche and rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but all are not riche &amp; rightuous, it is good inoughe if we be rightuous whether we be riche or poore. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer be awaye, rightuouſnes maye not be away.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the firſt parte of this ſermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>¶ The ſeconde parte.</head>
               <p>FVrthermore accordyng to my promes, I will ſpeake of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſorte of men, that are rich in themſelues and not in god. Of this ſorte of riche men was this riche man of whom Chriſte made this parable. Of ſuch ſorte of riche men the holy ſcripture is plentyfull, and the whole worlde is not emptie. Of that ſorte of men Sainte paule admoniſſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Timotheus his dyſciple .j. Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy .vj. Charge them (ſaith he) whiche are riche in this worlde, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not<pb facs="tcp:150659:15"/>highe mynded, nor to truſte in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certen riches: and in theſame chapiter he ſpekethe alſo, of ſuche riche men. They (ſaith he) that wilbe riche, (that is to ſay to themſelues &amp; not to God) fall into temptacion and ſnares of the Deuell, and to many folyſhe and noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome luſtes, whiche drawe men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perdicion and deſtruction &amp;c. Here ye ſee partly in what caſe they are that are riche in themſelues and not in god. Paule calleth them the riche of this worlde, becauſe they looke for none other riches of the other worlde. They maye well bee called the riche of this worlde, for they ſhalbe poore beggers in the other worlde, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>they make no preparacion here, that they may be riche there. A liuely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of ſuche a riche man is ſetfurth by our ſauiour Chriſte himſelfe in the xii. of Saint Luke &amp; that by a parable. The grounde (ſaith Chriſte) of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten riche man brought forth plentiful frutes, and he thought within himſelf ſaiyng, what ſhal I do? becauſe I haue<pb facs="tcp:150659:16"/>no rome where to beſtowe my frutes? And he ſaied, thus wil I do I wyl de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye my barnes and buylde greater and therein wil I gather all my good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that are growen vnto me and I wyll ſaie vnto my ſoule: Soule thou haſte muche goodes layed vp in ſtore for many yeares, take thyne eaſe, eate, drinke, be mery. But God ſaied vnto hym: Thou foole, this night they ſhall fetche away thy ſoule againe from the then whoſe ſhall thoſe thynges be, whiche thou haſte prouided?</p>
               <p>Here is many wounderous thinges in this parable to be conſidered, if men of thys worlde ware ſo wyſe to conſider them in tyme, no doubte of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they ſhall conſider it &amp; that depe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and erneſtly, but all to late, all to late I ſay. It ware very expedient for all menne, and namely for ſuche as be laden with worldly, goodes, riches, Dignities &amp; promocions, &amp; that nowe in tyme, whyle tyme is, for that tyme wyll awaye ſhortely ere a manne be ware. It ware good to beware in
<pb facs="tcp:150659:16"/>tyme I ſaie, for after that tyme, it is to late to be beware, It is to late to be wyſe, for al thy wareneſſe and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome will not helpe then. Lette them be ware nowe ere it be ouer late. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the olde prouerbe: happie is he that can be ware by another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hurte, he is wiſe, that can learne wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by another manes foliſhnes. He is happie that can learne to be ware in tyme. All menne, that haue godly witte and vnderſtandynge, maye be ware howe they vſe their gooddes and their liues, by theſe .ij. men ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furth in theſe .ij. parables, to all men to learne by, howe to haue heare in this worlde there goodes, and howe to ſpende them. Of the one mencion is made in Luke .xij. Chapiter, And of the other in the
.xvj. Chapiter of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Euangeliſte. I wyll begynne nowe with the fyrſte.</p>
               <p>¶ I haue reherſed vnto you, alredy the texte, which begynneth thus. The grounde of a certeyne Ryche manne broughte furthe plentifull frutes. &amp;c.<pb facs="tcp:150659:17"/>Here is to be marked, the greate and infinite goodnes of god that gaue ſuch aboundaunce of al erthly thynges, to this vnthankefull man, that dothe not once conſider the abundant goodnes of God towardes hym, nor yet is he merciful towardes his neighbors, but forgate his bounde dewtie, bothe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes god and his neighbours, and remembred onely hymſelf. Marke the wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtory or parable, marke what this man ſaied, and marke alſo what he dyd, Marke I ſay, for al men oughte to beware, either of ſuche ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges or doynges, for the prouerbe is true: ſo do: ſo haue. Say and do as this man dyd, and it ſhalbe ſayed and done to you, as it was ſayed and done vnto him. Marke this man well, with his ſaiynges and doynges, for euen ſo, it ſhalbe ſaied and done vnto you as was ſaied and done vnto hym. Firſte what ſaied he? what dyd he? He ſaied, what ſhall I do, becauſe I haue no roume where to beſtowe my frutes. And he ſaied: thus will I do: I wil deſtroy my<pb facs="tcp:150659:17"/>barnes, and buyld greater, and therin will I gather all my goodes that are growen to me. &amp;c. Here ye heare part of this mannes ſaiynges, and ſee his doynges, not without his thinkinges. He ſaied, what ſhall I do? Was this euill ſaid? It had not been euill ſaid, if the meanyng of his ſaiyng had been good. Euery man ought to examyne his awne conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: ſaiyng to hymſelf, what ſhall I do? This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſaiyng maie be borne with in part, but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the whole, with the meanyng, all is naught. He ſaieth: what ſhall I do. His meanyng was naught, his awne wordes declare no leſſe. He meaneth not, when he ſaieth, what ſhall I do, accordyng to Goddes will, and to the comfort of my neighbor. His meaning was altogether to get, to kepe, and to ſpende, all for his awne pleaſure, all for his awne profite. He regarded nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his dutie towardes God, nor yet towardes his neighbour. He made no reconyng, whence his aboundance of his goodes came, who gaue that plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whoſe goodes thei were, and how<pb facs="tcp:150659:18"/>thei ought to be beſtowed. His mynd was ſet another waie, how he ſhould kepe theſe his goodes, wher he ſhould beſtowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his mind was occupied in pullyng doune thoſe thynges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were to litle for his purpoſe, &amp; to build grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, &amp; to lacke no rome, where to lay al ſuche goodes, as wer growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him as God had ſent, geuen, or lent hym. Was this an euill thyng, either to ſpeake or to do? to buyld greater hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to make greater romes, wher god ſendeth ſuche great plentie? Nay truly. Herein was his faulte, that all that he either thought, ſaid or did, was thought, ſaid and doen, to none other end, but al for hymſelf. He neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded his duetie towardes God, nor yet towardes his neighbor. We heare nothyng of his thoughtes, ſaiynges &amp; doinges, that his goodes came-fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god and ought to haue been receiued with thankeſgeuyng, and alſo to haue been beſtowed, accordyng to God the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wil. We heare tell of none of all theſe thynges, neither by his though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, wordes nor dedes, but he thought<pb facs="tcp:150659:18"/>ſaid and did, al thynges, accordyng to his awne will, to his awne pleaſure, &amp; for his awne profit. He compted al his goodes and ſubſtaunce his awne, gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto himſelf onely, and onely (as he toke it) to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his awne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and profite. This I will do, this I will ſay, ſaith he to hymſelf. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred not, what the will of god was what he ſhould ſaie, &amp; what he ſhould do; but he ſaied: thus wil I do, &amp; thus will I ſaie. Be there not many now a daies, that bothe dooe and ſaie: euen as this man did and ſaied. If a manne would conſider the doynges &amp; the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges, of many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now a daies, ſhuld we not thinke ye, finde them as mad &amp; as marueilous, as this mannes doyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; ſaiynges were? Should we not perceiue by ſuche ſaiynges and doyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges their imaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and thoughtes to be as vain, as mad and as vngodly, as this mannes were. Should not a man markyng theſe thinges, perceiue that men now a daies, be as vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to God, as this man was? Should not a man finde ſuche now a daies, as
<pb facs="tcp:150659:19"/>hath receiued ſuche aboundaunce of goodes, of ſubſtaunce, of honours and promocions at Goddes hand, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde their dueties in theſe thynges, towardes God and their neighbour, as litle as this manne did. But what nedeth me to go furth and dilate this matter at length. Loke vpon mennes maners, and ye ſhall ſe, that thei now a daies, paſſe this man, bothe in their doynges &amp; ſaiynges, and alſo by their imaginacions, whiche be ſeen vnto vs by their ſaiynges and doynges, to bee nothyng behynd hym. Thynke ye not that thoſe menne, beyng either equall with this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or paſſyng hym, in their imaginacions, ſaiynges and doynges, ſhall not all theſe heare alſo by the mouthe of God, ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as this man did, ſaied vnto hym? Yes, truely ſhall thei. Nowe what the mouthe of God ſpake to this man then, and no leſſe to oure menne of like condicions now ye ſhall heare hereafter. Butere I paſſe, I muſte reherſe vnto you, one ſaiyng of this mannes more, and then I wil come to Gods ſaiyng, for,
<pb facs="tcp:150659:19"/>when we haue all ſaied, we muſte bee content to geue God licence alſo, to ſaie his mynd, for ſurely ſo will he do, wil we: nil we. And we will not heare hym here, we muſt and ſhal heare him there, with a worſe will and leſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. I will returne again, to that one ſaiyng of this man that is behind, and then will I tell you what God ſaith. This man ſaied thus, ſaieth the text: And I will ſaie vnto my ſoule (ſaieth he) ſoule, thou haſte muche goodes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed vp in ſtore for many yeres. Take thyne eaſe, eate, drinke, be mery. Firſt and formoſte ye muſt marke, who it is, that ſpeaketh on this faſhion, it is the riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that heare afore is deſcribed he that had ſuche abundance of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that he wiſt not where to lay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he that had no Godly regarde to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe them, but all his mynde was, in gettyng, in gatheryng, in hourdyng, and laiyng vp in ſtore, for lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tyme to come. Suche menne thus full, hauyng all thyng after their awne mind, then thei begin to ſaie to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, in their awne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiptes: ſoule thou haſt much<pb facs="tcp:150659:20"/>goodes laied vp in ſtore for many ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Marke here the imaginacion of ſuche riche men, thei wene, through the multitude of their ſubſtaunce, to liue many yeres and daies. This man was of that opinion, becauſe he had ſuche aboundaunce of goodes, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed hymſelf many yeres, to make mery in, and to leade a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlemanly life, bothe a pleaſaunt and a long. But he made his reconyng (as the Prouerbe is) without his hoſte: and ſo he is fain to recon again. His many yeres were ſone run ouer. He was not ſuffered to liue, the ſpace of an whole day. He pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed hymſelf, many other thynges mo: whiche came to as good effect and paſſe, as this thyng did. He ſaied alſo: take thine eaſe, eate drinke and be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Where is that long eaſe that was promiſed, with that delicacie in eatyng and that pleaſauntneſſe in drynkyng. Where is become, the careleſſe life, wherein there ſhould be nothyng, but mirthe and ioye, and makyng merie: ſettyng the Cocke vpon houpe, and all ſhould bee well. All together is<pb facs="tcp:150659:20"/>turned: arſie, verſie. There came one ſodainly, vnloked for, and alſo vnwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, that marred all the playe. Who was that? Truly GOD. Why, is it come to his courſe, to ſpeake nowe? Yea ſurely. When men haue ſhewed their vanitie, then will God ſhewe his veritie. Men doo take their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when thei bee here hauyng all thyng after their awn luſtes, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme commeth, that God dooeth appoyncte, he will take then his luſte and pleaſure, and will bryng theim: <hi>cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis</hi> in a wilde wanion, and he will tell them a newe tale then, farre vnlike to their tale, wherein thei pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed themſelfes long life and wel to fare. But when God beginneth to ſpeake, then thei begin to holde their peace. Why will God begin once to ſpeake? Yea, that he will truely. A practiſe of Goddes ſpeakyng, wee learne here, in this preſent place of Scripture. When this riche manne had talked ful his bely, after his awn fanſie, thinkyng al thyng ſhould come<pb facs="tcp:150659:21"/>to paſſe, euen as he had imagined it. Euen when he had went he had been mooſte ſure, he was ſoneſt deceiued. I told you, he made his reconyng with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his hooſte. His hooſte (whiche is God, to whom all reconynges muſte be made truely) called hym to a newe reconyng, he made hym make a newe compt. It foloweth in the texte. But God ſaied vnto hym: thou foole, this night thei ſhal fetche awaie thy ſoule again fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe thynges bee, whiche thou haſt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? It is the faſhion of GOD, to call ſuche menne to a reare compt. Is God ſo ſharpe in his woordes, that he will call as many as he findeth in this caſe, fooles? Yea truly, this is his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and thus will he do. I feare me then, that a greate many of our wiſe men, at whoſe wiſedome the worlde wondereth now, will bee called foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les then. I feare me, that a greate no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of noble men, whoſe nobilitie the worlde worſhippeth, will bee proued fooles then. I feare me, that a greate nomber of our Iudges and Iuſtices,<pb facs="tcp:150659:21"/>whoſe aucthoritie is not ſmall in the worlde, will bee proued fooles then. I feare me, that a greate many of our learned clergie, whoſe learnyng is in no ſmall reputacion: will bee founde fooles then. What ſhall I nede to run ouer, all the ſtates and ſortes of men: ſeeyng that all menne, of whatſoeuer ſtate or condicion thei be, if thei do, as this fooliſhe riche man did, no doubte the mouthe of God, here in this place of Scripture, calleth all the many of theim fooles. All ſuche men that thus liueth, and ſo dieth, be created fooles by Goddes awne mouth, whiche cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth theim fooles, becauſe thei vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, here in this life, ſo like fooles. Thei liue fooles, thei ſhall die fooles (except thei repent) and ſhall ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain fooles: and ſhall go to their iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fooles, and after that, thei ſhal go to the deuill, like fooles as thei be. Men compt now a daies, none fooles but ſuche as we are fooles cotes, coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes, eares &amp; belles. But I feare me, that this manne that our ſauiour Chriſte ſpeaketh of in this Parable,<pb facs="tcp:150659:22"/>with all thoſe that are like vnto hym in condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, be more fooles then thei, for all their cockes combes, eares, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. What if a man ſhould aſke but a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a ſimilitude: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were worthie to bee called a foole that had in his awne poſſeſſion of his awne patrimonie, a .M. pound lande, and if that manne hauyng this thouſand pound land, would chaunge his thouſande pounde of patrimonie, for an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred ſhillynges of copie hold lande, onely to haue it <hi>ad uoluntatem domini?</hi> Were not this man worthie to be called of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a foole, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to weare a Cockes combe and a bel. &amp;c. wer he neuer ſo wiſe compted. Suche fooles almoſt are al the whole worlde. Doeth not all the worlde (for the moſt part) chaunge heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for yearthly thynges, perpetuall thynges, for tranſitorie thynges, the life euerlaſting, for this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life. Is not this foole as wiſe as thei? What will ye make of a foole, or how will ye diſcerne or knowe a foole, but by that he doth like a foole, and as no wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150659:22"/>would doo, he will not geue his bable for a Kynges raund ſome, he knoweth not what is good &amp; what is euill. He wil leaue the beſt and choſe the worſt. He knoweth not (as the Prouerbe ſaieth) cheſe from chalke, and therfore he is iudged a foole, and is a foole in deede, and if he neuer ware wiſer, he ſhall die a foole in very deede. Now I pray you, do not thei, that receiue goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, richeſſe, honors, offices, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocious of this worlde, &amp; either abuſe them, or be vnthankfull to god for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſo for theſe vncertein &amp; vnſtable goodes, riches, honors, offices and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocions of this falſe flattryng world, do for lacke of godly wiſedom and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng hede here in tyme, loſe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng, ſure and permanent, goodes, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, honors, offices and promocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Be not theſe thinke ye, thoſe that the mouth of God, doth openly, plainly, &amp; ſharpely here in this place cal fooles? yes truly, &amp; ſhalbe ſerued like fooles, as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion, &amp; knittyng vp of this aforeſaid parable of our ſauior Chriſt doth plainly &amp; vndoubtedly pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<pb facs="tcp:150659:23"/>and declare to all maner of perſones, none excepted: ſaiyng. So it is with him, that gathereth riches to himſelf, and is not riche towardes god. Heare the mouthe of truthe, yea, the truth it ſelf pronounceth, what ſhall come of all ſuche as abuſe, and be vnthankfull to God for ſuche thynges, and vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to their neighbors, with their goodes, richeſſe, honours, offices, and promocions of this world, and regard not ſuche thynges, as bee prepared for good and godly men, in the world that is to come. I would fain if it wer poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, ſette furthe ſome thyng, before theſe worldly wiſe mennes iyes, that thei might clerely ſe their awne ſtate, that thei bee here in, in this preſent worlde. I cannot imagine how better to ſhewe them their ſtate, (if it be not rather worthy to be called a fall) then to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare their whole life, to men that dreame, pleaſaunt and profitable dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and do thinke themſelfes, for the tyme ſo well, as thei can imagin them ſelfes, that thei cannot be better, and ſo long as that ſwete ſlepe dooth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue,<pb facs="tcp:150659:23"/>ſo long are thei (as thei imagin) mooſte happie. But when thei awake out of that dreame, and perceiue al the matter, to bee turned to a dreamyng matter, all that their felicitie, is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to miſery, all their ioye, is turned to ſorowe, and ſo to conclude, al thyng is turned topſie turuie. Truly, truly, if the worldly mynded manne, whoſe hart, mynd and al, is ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worldly thynges, his ſtate, the ende conſidered is euen like the ſtate of a dreamer, or a dreamyng man, that is in the middes of his pleaſaunt &amp; profitable dreames. He thynketh all is well, and he hath al thinges after his awne hartes luſt, and ſuppoſeth all thynges ſo to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. But alacke alacke, he is farre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, euen as a dremyng man is. For when God ſhall take ſuche men, from this vain and dreamyng life, then ſhal thei, truly ſe and perceiue, with their awne greate hurte, becauſe thei will not conſider it in tyme, that al was as vain, as vain dreames, that thei tooke for bothe ſtable and profitable, which doeth but make fooles fain for a tyme.
<pb facs="tcp:150659:24"/>Therefore I would aduiſe, all ſuche worldly men to bee wiſe in tyme, and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what Eccleſiaſtes teacheth them in the .xij. Chapiter of his boke, ſaiyng: <hi>Vanitas uanitatum (dixit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes) &amp; oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>auanitas.</hi> Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſaieth, he can ſee nothyng here in this world, but all was vanitie, vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vanitie, fondneſſe, fondneſſe, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheneſſe, fooliſheneſſe. Now what is all your greate richeſſe, high honours offices and promocions? Are not all vanities. When your dreamyng tyme is out, ye ſhal then truly perceiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee verie vanities. Yea, and worſe then vanities, if either ye abuſe them, or be vnthankfull to God for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and help not your neighbors with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thei ſhalbe vnto you dampnable vanities. Now I beſeche god for his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, to geue vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace, to vſe well their riches, high honors, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and promocions, and to be thank<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full to god for them, and charitable to their neighbors with them. And ſo to vſe theſe thynges (whiche of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes if thei be abuſed) bee but vanities, to<pb facs="tcp:150659:24"/>vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I ſaie) as inſtrumentes, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by thei may pleaſe god, &amp; profite their neighbors, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here frendes by the right vſing of theſe worldly va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nities, whiche maie receiue them into euerlaſtyng habitacions. Now here I haue ſhewed you of ſuche riche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as are riche to themſelfes, &amp; not to God, Better it wer for theim to be warned here in tyme, then to tary to lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, vntil thei for lacke of warnyng come to hel, where warnyng will not ſerue. As it chaunced vnto this riche man, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye now ſhall heare, in this Parable folowyng, whiche is now for lacke of takyng hede in tyme: da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned in hell, &amp; fain would haue remedy, but becauſe he ſeketh it to late, none wilbe found.</p>
               <trailer>&amp; Here endeth the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part of this Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>NOwe to the Parable. There was a certain riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was clothed in Purple &amp; fine white, &amp; fared delicioufly euery day, &amp; there was a begger named Lazarus, whiche lay at his gate full of ſores, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiryng to be refreſhed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes whiche fell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the riche mans borde, &amp;<pb facs="tcp:150659:25"/>no man gaue vnto hym. The Dogges came alſo, &amp; licked his ſores. Here, in the beginnyng of this parable, Chriſt did ſet furthe to the Iewes, to whom he preached then, and no leſſe to vs, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this his doctrine is preached now two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the which, one was a riche man, and the other a poore begger, by the whiche twoo, he ſetteth furthe by
<hi>antitheſin,</hi> the felicitie of this worlde in thone, and the miſery of this world in the other. That is, in this riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſet furthe, the life that is compted onely happie in this worlde. In the poore man, is ſet furth the life, that is compted moſte vnhappie, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this worlde. Firſt, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider earneſtly, the ſtate of theſe twoo men, beyng bothe here in this worlde: and alſo their ſtates in the world to come. Theſe thynges are to bee conſidered earneſtly of vs, euen now while tyme is, leſt perchaunce we deferre it, til it be to late, as this riche man did, as ye maie well conſider in this Parable. Here we maie learne alſo to conſider not thynges that be onely preſent, but<pb facs="tcp:150659:25"/>rather thendes of al thynges. The life of the riche manne was compted beſt, and the poore mannes life worſte, but the ende ſheweth farre otherwiſe. Let vs not folowe the faſhion and maner of men of this worlde, whiche care li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for the ende, ſo that thei now maie haue the pleaſaunt life, that this rich man had, nothyng at all conſideryng the ende, what chaunced vnto hym af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life was paſt. This aforeſaied man, is named here riche, &amp; was riche in deede, and was compted happie and fortunate, for he lacked nothyng, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che belonged to leade a pleaſaunt life withall. He was clothed in Purple, and fine white, and fared deliciouſly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery daie. In theſe two thynges, that is, in coſtly and precious raiment, and delicate fare, is comprehended al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that are to this preſent life, either pleaſaunt or delectable. Vnder theſe twoo kyndes, that is, purple &amp; white, is comprehended, all maner of coſtly and ſumpteous apparel, whether it be linen, or wollen. And by theſe wordes he fared deliciouſly euery daie, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande,
<pb facs="tcp:150659:26"/>that he had abundance of al coſtly and delicate meates and drinkes We rede not here, that this riche man was condempned in hell, for his coſtly raiment, and his delicate fare, but that he hauyng ſuche abundance of theim bothe, could not finde in his hart, that poore Lazarus ſhould haue any parte with hym. All thei that are coſtly ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed, and fare delicatly, are not conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pned, ſo that thei kepe theim within their limites and boundes, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gette not theim that lacke, euen their caſtraime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and their ſcrappes alſo of their table. Here are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thei, that are to theimſelfes to libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, yea, to prodigall, bothe in raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and fare, regardyng not, what thei ſpende vpon theimſelfes, painperyng vp their awne bodies, &amp; in the meane ſeaſon, are altogether vnliberall, and ſtarke nigardes to the poore and nedy and can finde in their hartes, to ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die at their gates, bothe for hunger and alſo for cold. Thus did this riche manne, to the poore begger Lazarus: therfore he is in hel for his labor. And
<pb facs="tcp:150659:26"/>what learne we by this riche mannes doyng, but to bewart, leſt wee doyng like, ſhall haue like, euen as he hath. For, therfore is this rich man ſet here to teache vs to be ware by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. Here I ſaie, euery manne muſte kepe himſelf, within his limites and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and ſo there ſhalbe no man damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, either for rayment, or for coſtly fare, ſo that men bee beneficiall to the poore. But bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des be broken, limites be ouer trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there is almoſte no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone that kepeth hymſelf within his limites or boundes: there is almoſt no man, that can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with his awne ſtate, neither in raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor yet in fare. The yeoman will approche to the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemannes ſtate, the gentleman to the knightes ſtate, the knight to the lords ſtate, and ſo furth on: and not onely in raiment, but alſo in fare. And that ſee the ſeruauntes, and thei paſſe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree alſo: and ſo euery man is out of order. O that men would be content, to fare and go, euery man after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and beware of climyng. And alſo if euery man would beware of exceſſe<pb facs="tcp:150659:27"/>in all thynges, the pouerties nedes might bee releued in all thynges. For there is more ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſuperfluous rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſuperfluous fare (I holde my peace from ſuperfluous gamyng, and ſuperfluous giftes geuyng) in Englande, then would ſerue to the neceſſities, of the very nedy of al En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande. Nowe yet a litle to the texte. There is a certain riche man. &amp;c. We reade not that this riche manne, gatte his goodes euil, but he bothe kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euill, and ſpent them not well. I rede not, that he was a bribe taker, nor an extorcioner, nor a re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t raiſer, nor a fine taker, nor a leaſemonger, nor an vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, nor a piller, or poller of the poore, nor a falſe purchaſer. In ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma, I rede not that he gatte his goodes euil, but that he ſpent theim all vpon his awne perſone, and after his awne pleaſure, and not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore, after the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God. The text ſaith, this man was riche, but it was to hymſelf, and to the world, and altogether after the worldly eſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and alone afore the worlde and worldly men, but he was<pb facs="tcp:150659:27"/>a very miſer and poore begger, before God and all godly men. Here ye haue heard of this rich man, in what felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and pleaſure, he ledde his life, how that he was compted happie and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, emong all other here, and as he liued honourably, ſo he died to the world honorably, and was buried ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norably. All his life was honorable, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the very graue, but to what honor he came afterward beyng dedde ye ſhall heare hereafter. Firſt, ye ſhal heare of the poore begger Lazarus life howe miſerably he liued, in a worldly reſpect: as it foloweth in the text. And there was a certein begger, named Lazarus, whiche laie at his gate full of ſores, deſiryng to be refreſhed with the cromes, whiche fel from the riche mannes borde, and no man gaue vnto hym, the dogges came alſo and licked his ſores. Nowe herken here of this poore beggers life. There was a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain begger named Lazarus, a man as farre drouned in miſerie, as the riche man was in felicitie: this manne was not onely poore and a begger, but alſo<pb facs="tcp:150659:28"/>a miſerable begger, as far out of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes reputacion, as the riche man was in eſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This man was as poore in lackyng, as the other was riche in hauyng. This man lacked, euen verie neceſſaries, where as the other abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſuperfluouſnes. This miſer (as the worlde taketh miſers) had neither houſe nor home, neither coate nor goune, he lacked neither ſores nor hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who would not ſaie, that he was moſte vnhappie of all other, that euer liued in the worlde? Who would ſaie that doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, bothe theſe mennes lifes, that is to ſay, this riche mannes life, &amp; the poore beggers life, but that the riche manne was euen a verie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, full of felicitie, and the begger a paterne of very miſery. Thone was riche, the other a beggar and poore, the one had abundance of all thynges and the other the lacke of all thynges. The one had to many houſes, &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neuer a one. Thone had to much meate and drinke, and the other neuer a whit. The one was ſound and mery and the other ſicke and ſorie. The one<pb facs="tcp:150659:28"/>was all to well clothed: and the other all together naked. Here a man maie ſe a liuely exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of worldly felicitie &amp; of worldly miſery. What man ſeyng &amp; conſideryng, bothe theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes lifes, but would ſaie, thone wer altogether happie, &amp; thother altogether vnhappy The ſtate of this riche man is highly eſtemed, with all that be but men, and a lonely worldly men, and yet it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng leſſe, then ſo eſtemed of God, &amp; godly men. As our ſauior Chriſt ſaith in Luke .xvi. chap. That that is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtemed emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gmen: is abhominable in the ſight of god. He ſaith not onely it is litle or lightly ſet by, in the ſight of God, but it is abhominable in the ſight of god. Marke here, that all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, all dignities, all promocions, all offices, &amp; al riches, whiche, although thei be neuer ſo highly eſtemed in the worlde of worldly men: if thei bee not rightly vſed, vnto the honor of God, and charitably ordered, to the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and wealthe of Goddes people, the ſtate of theim that poſſeſſe theim: although it bee in the ſight of menne,
<pb facs="tcp:150659:29"/>highly eſtemed and honourable, in the ſight of GOD and Godly menne, is bothe horrible &amp; abhominable. What ſhall wee then ſaie? Shall thynges of this preſent worlde, continue ſtill in their eſtimacion, in another world al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as menne eſteme theim here, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thei bee good or bad? This mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is clerely ſet furthe, to all mennes iyes that will ſee, in this preſent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, of this riche manne, and poore Lazarus. Conſider the ende of thoſe twoo perſones, and then ye ſhall ſee, and that euidently, that the matter is farre otherwiſe. Sodeinly, death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, turneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter vpſide doune. Death commyng to the riche man, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth an ende of all his felicitie &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, wherin he was thought to be ſo happie. Death on the other ſide, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng to this poore man, is the ende of all ſorowes and miſeries. O that the world, whiche is ſo blinded in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanities: would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider this thyng bothe hartly and earneſty. Then men ſhould not be ſo forgetful, and ſo litle remember the ſtate, that is to come in<pb facs="tcp:150659:29"/>another worlde. It is not for naught, that that good man, Ieſus the ſonne of Siracke in his boke, whiche is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Eccleſiaſticus, in the .vij. Chapit. doth warne euery man of this thyng, ſaiyng: Sonne, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thy laſt ende, and thou ſhalt neuer doo amiſſe. The lacke of this remembran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in tyme, is the cauſe, that ſo many menne go to the deuill. If that we would, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and often reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, what is to come in another worlde, after this preſent life, we ſhould neuer ſo forget, (as we now doo) neither our duetie to God, nor yet to our neighbour. We ſhould not ſet ſo muche by worldly vanities as we do: we ſhould not ſo lightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard heauenly and eternall thynges, and ſo highly eſteme worldly thynges as we do. Remember therfore thy laſt ende, and what thy ſtate ſhalbee after this preſent life. Remember (I ſaie, yea, bothe earneſtly and ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that remembraunce ſhall cauſe thee to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chue vice, and to folowe and embrace vertue. Beware by thexample of this riche man, whiche delighted and had<pb facs="tcp:150659:30"/>ſomuche pleaſure, that he thought not once of deathe, and of his ſtate after deathe. And therefore is he nowe, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to late) taught with his awne dampnacion, to teache other in tyme, by his example, the waie to ſaluacion. He was ſo full of richeſſe, that he had no regard to pouertie. He had ſomuch wealth, that he regarded nothyng at all poore mennes miſerie. Poore La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus deſired no deinties, but onely to releue his hunger, with the cromes or ſcrappes, that were lefte at this riche manne's table, but no man gaue vnto him. By like there was an vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houſe, that neither one nor other, could finde in his harte, to geue this begger ſome almoſe. I doubt not, but euery manne within the dores had to muche, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dogges and all. But there was nothyng without the doores, for the poore nedy and hungrie, but hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſmall eaſe. Yea, the very dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were more mercifull, then either their maiſter, or maiſtres, or houſhold for thei delte their almoſe vpon hym. The dogges (ſaith the text) came and<pb facs="tcp:150659:30"/>licked his ſores. Suche maiſter, ſuche ſeruauntes, is commonly ſene. This man was altogether liberall, yea, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall vpon hymſelf and his, after his awne luſte and pleaſure: but concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the poore nedy, and Goddes luſt and pleaſure, he was eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a very ſtarke nigard. Well, this man liued here all in his felicitie, and ſo did poore La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus, euen in his miſerie. But nowe commeth death (as I haue ſaied) and turneth all topſie turuie. It foloweth in the texte. And it fortuned, that the begger died, and was caried by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels into Abrahams boſome. It chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (ſaieth the texte) that the begger died. That begger (I ſaie) that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regarded whiles he liued, but god ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed howe muche he regarded hym, in that that his angelles brought him in to Abrahams boſome. The riche man wold not once vouchſafe, to take hym into his houſe, to releue hym, but god doth vouchſafe to take hym, to ſuche a place, where is euerlaſtyng felicitie &amp; glory. Let vs conſider, what maner of departing had Lazarus fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world<pb facs="tcp:150659:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>Death to this good and godly begger yea, to all godly men, is a greate bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. For it deliuereth all ſuche, from innumerable euils, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it wer men that had been long in a ſharpe priſon, from greate affliccion, to great refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng. Therefore it is no pein nor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, for a good and godly man to die. For to hym death is the very way and paſſage, to euerlaſtyng ioye and high felicitie. This poore man is ded (ſaith the text). He is ded I graunt, but not ſo dedde, or with ſuche a death, as the wicked men vſe to die, but after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faſhion, of the whiche the holy man Iob, the .Lxvi Chap. ſpeaketh on ſaiyng: The death of his ſainctes (ſaith he) is very precious in the lordes ſight This poore Lazarus ſoule was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, not of one Angell, but of many ſaieth the text. Whether did thei cary it? Into Abrahams boſome, that is, in to euerlaſtyng ioye &amp; reſt in the lorde. Whiche place, ſome men call Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, after Chriſtes ſaiyng to the thefe hangyng on his right hand, whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired hym, to haue hym in his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce,
<pb facs="tcp:150659:31"/>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould come into his kyngdome, Luke .xxiij. where Chriſte ſaith vnto him: this daie ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe. Some call this place the hande of the Lorde, as it is written in the .iij. Chap. of the boke of Sapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. The ſoules of the righteous are in the hande of the Lorde. Marke here, that although mencion is made, that the ſoules of good, godly, &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous perſones, be ſafe enough, either in Abrahams boſome, in Paradiſe, in the hande of the Lorde, or in heauen. And I doubte not but that thei haue, ſuche glory and felicitie: as .S. Paule to the Cori. ſpeaketh of in the .i. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle the .ij. Chap. ſaiyng, that mannes iye hath not ſeen, and theare hath not heard, neither haue entered into the hart of man, the thynges whiche God hath prepared for them that loue him. But to tell you what glory thei haue what thei do, and where thei be: I can nomore tel, then the ſcripture telleth. I let God alone with all ſuche ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, as Chriſte, his Apoſtles, and the prophetes, hath not reueled and made<pb facs="tcp:150659:32"/>manifeſt to vs in holy ſcripture. Now I doubt not but Abrahames boſome, is the place wherin all the elected and choſen of God, whiche doo truely fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe Abrahams faith, do reſt in. But nowe where that place is, I knowe not, and therfore I will not go about to determyne a thyng that I knowe not. Lette vs not bee muche carefull, where that place is, but rather let vs bee carefull, how wee ſhall come the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There was neuer time, but that God had appoyncted a place for his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to reſt in. Afore Chriſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, that place was called, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Abraham: but now it is called heauen, the houſe of the eternall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as .S. Paule witneſſeth in his .ij Epiſtle, the .v. Chap to the Cori. For we knowe (ſaieth he) that if our year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy manſion of this dwellyng wer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, we haue a buyldyng of God, an habitacion, not made with handes but eternall in heauen. Alſo Chriſt in Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xiiij. ſpeakyng of the ſame thyng, ſaieth: In my fathers houſe there bee many dwellyng places. And the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:150659:32"/>Chriſt ſafeth alſo in Ihou .xii. Where I am (ſaith he) there ſhal my miniſter bee alſo. Paule alſo in his Epiſtle to the Philippians the .i. Cha. Deſireth to bee loſed, and to bee with Chriſte. Now here ye haue hard thende of this poore begger, beyng righteous before God, what came to hym after his deth and departyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his body. Although he were of no reputacion before the worlde, yet he was highly regarded before God. In this good poore man, beyng in the ſight of God righteous: all good, godly, and righteous poore beggers, and men of ſmall reputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, make greate comfort, vnto whom the ioye &amp; felicitie of the life to come, ſhal recompenſe the ſorowe and miſerie, that is in this life all comen and paſt. Here ye heard of Lazarus death, and what chanced vnto him after his deth. Now ſhall ye heare of the riche man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes death. Why? do ſuche men die, as well as poore men doo? So well? No God knoweth, thei die all doubtles, but how well thei die, and how well cometh to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after their death, marke
<pb facs="tcp:150659:33"/>well this parable, and ye ſhall know. It foloweth in the parable. The rich man alſo died and was buried. Is he ded in deede? How chaunced he died? It was not (I truſte) for lacke of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes? For he had to many. It was not for lacke of meate and drynke, for he had to muche. Why? will not gay and coſtly clothes &amp; delicate meates, kepe men from death? No, rather I feare me thei help men to death. Then I ſe that neither coſtly araye, nor delicate fare, nor abundaunce of goodes, nor excellencie of dignities, nor greatnes in office, nor yet nobleneſſe of birthe: will kepe any man from death. For as ſone dieth the riche man with his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and his coſtly raiment, and with his delicate fare, as the poore manne with his pouertie, courſe raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and homely fare. Aſſone die thei in digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and greate Offices, as other that haue none of them bothe. Aſſone dieth the noble, as the baſe borne. Aſſone dieth the Prelate, as the Pulter, as ſone dieth the prieſte as the clerke. &amp;c. For as Paule ſaieth to the Hebrues,<pb facs="tcp:150659:33"/>ix. Chapiter. It is appoyncted vnto al men, that thei ſhall once die. And the olde ſaiyng is true: There is nothyng more certain then death, but there is nothyng more vncertain, then thoure of death. Now to the text again. The riche alſo died. &amp;c. Why? Is he dedde that promiſed hymſelf ſo long tyme to liue? He is dedde. But is he dedde in deede? Yea truly. What ſhall we then ſaie? what? Mary if he wer, as many of our riche menne be now a daies, I knowe what men bee wont to ſaie, I would not that thei ſhould ſo ſaye. What (I praie thee) bee thei wont to ſaie, when ſuche riche coueteous men die? What? Euen thus plumpe out. The deuill in hell be with theim. Let theim geſſe again, if thei had ſaied ſo when this riche man died, and had la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed any wager on it, it maie fortune thei ſhould haue won. But what ſhal we ſaie? God haue mercy on his ſoule that wer but loſt labor. For God wil haue no mercie vpon theim that be in hell. For ſcripture ſaieth: in hell is no redempcion. What ſhall I ſaie, God
<pb facs="tcp:150659:34"/>haue mercie on poore Lazarus ſoule? That alſo is loſt labor, for God hath mercie on him all redy. It is now paſt God haue mercy of all chriſten ſoules matter, when men de departed all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Praie here, and that in time, for to praie when men be ded, it is to late. It foloweth in the text. And was buried. What matter was this, that he was buried. It is a matter, for we read no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng of Lazarus buriyng, and yet I doubte not but that he was buried. Here is mencion made of this riche mannes buriyng: by that is ſignified, that his buriall was like, as al his like was compted, that is moſte honorable and I doubt not, but ſo was his buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all alſo. Moreouer, I doubte not but this riche man, had Diriges, Maſſes, Trintals, and prieſtes enough to ſaie Maſſes for hym. He neither lacked ſingyng nor ringing, chimyng nor tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, if ſuche thynges were vſed in thoſe daies. I doubt not but ther wer at his buriall, all the foure orders of Friers, with al the religious men and women, that could bee gotten for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.<pb facs="tcp:150659:34"/>There wer alſo many mourners with whoodes &amp; blacke gounes, with many a dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ye more, and ſo he was brought into the yearth moſte honour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rably. But poore Lazarus lacked us more but al this pomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he lacked not euerlaſtyng glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> had not this riche manne with all his trinkettes, wrought and dooen ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably, euerlaſtyng felicitie? Nor, ware that, for that is gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuche tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But where is he then? Where? Mary euen where he ſhould be, &amp; where he ſought in all his whole life for to be: Where is that? Euer in hell: for ſo ſaieth the text. What man, is al that ringyng and ſingyng, al that Maſſyng &amp; dirigyng, with crouchyng and kneelyng, with that bitter wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng and wailyng, with the Churche hangyng and greate offeryng, al toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſte? Yea truely; all was loſt to hym. For whoſoeuer founde aught; he found naught. Perchaunce ye wil ſay there were no ſuche thynges at that tyme, as is now vſed. I anſwere, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there were no ſuche thynges,<pb facs="tcp:150659:35"/>at that tyme vſed, yet I doubt not but there was then, as pratie deuices de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed by the Clergie, and receiued of the laitie, as wee haue ſeen in tymes paſt, and yet maie ſe, ſo that we wil ſe it. See ye not what pratie trickes bee in our this moſte knowyng tyme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighed into the bleſſed Communion for to get money withall? Now let vs returne again to this riche man, thus honorably buried, and ſo ſemeth vnto vnknowyng people of the worlde, to be in no worſe ſtate in another world, then he was in this world. But it wil bee founde farre otherwiſe, when the truthe is knowen.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the third part of this Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <p>IT foloweth in the text: And be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng in hell in tormentes, he lift vp his iyes, and ſawe Abraham a farre of, and Lazarus in his boſome, and he cried and ſaid: father Abraham haue mercie on me, and ſend Lazarus that he maie dippe the tippe of his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in water, and coole my tongue, for I am tormented in this flambe. But<pb facs="tcp:150659:35"/>Abraham ſaied: ſonne remember that thou in thy life tyme, receiuedeſt thy pleaſure, and contrarywiſe Lazarus receiued pain, but now he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, and thou art puniſhed. Ye haue heard here afore, how honourably this rich man (to the worlde) led his life, died and was alſo honorably buried. Now his honor is turned to horror, his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous ſtate, to an vnluckie ſtate. He liued here in all delicacie and pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, but he leadeth his life now in all miſeries and paines. Let vs conſider out of the texte here, in what miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble caſe this riche man is comen into nowe, after all his felicitie, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure taken in this worlde. Firſt, he is caſt into hell, whiche is a place for the that are perpetually da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned, in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che place, there is no hope of any deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery or ſaluacion. Furthermore, in that helle he is tormenred with firie flambes. We read no leſſe written by Eſate the Prophete, in his .lxvi. chap. Their wormes (ſaith he) ſhal not die, neither ſhall their fire bee quenched, and all fleſhe ſhall abhorre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſt<pb facs="tcp:150659:36"/>ſaieth alſo in Matthewe .xiij. Chapi. Thei ſhall caſt theim into a furnes of fire, there ſhalbe wailyng, &amp; gnaſhing of tethe. Yet more, this riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeth ſette before his iyes, poore Lazarus, whom in tymes paſte, he did nothyng regard, in greate and perpetuall feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie. This is no litle pain to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be dampned, to ſe them that were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, in compariſon to them, now ſo to be in perpetuall pleaſure, and them ſelfes in perpetuall pain, &amp; al through their awne folie. Furthermore, this riche manne is driuen to that nede, through his exceding pain, to begge of him, to whom in his life, he would not once vouchſafe to geue the cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of his table. He ſaith; ſend Lazarus that he may dippe the tippe of his finger in water, and coole my tongue, for I am tormented in this flambe. This is the very iudgement of God: whereby the pride and ſtoutneſſe of ſuche men, are wont to be puniſhed withall. For thei whiche were in plentie, and felicitie: contempned poore ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly ſoules in their miſery and beggarie, not hauyng pitie<pb facs="tcp:150659:36"/>vpon thein to helpe them, but thei de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed theim and iudged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to their companie. Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus doyng, doeth finde no leſſe at Goddes hande, and that by the right iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, bee brought to ſuche extreme neceſſitie and high miſerie, that thei would thanke God with al their har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that thoſe men, whom thei conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pned and ſette ſo litle by, would now vouchſafe once to geue theim one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar countenaunce, or ſpeake vnto the one familiar worde. It is (I ſaie) the very ordinaunce of God, that thei ſhalbee meaſured with the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that thei meaſured other withal for ſo ſaieth Chriſte in Matthewes Goſpell .vil. Chapi. with what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ye mete, with the ſame ſhal other men meaſure to you? There is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlous equalitie in god, for this riche man (not withſtandyng his bitter pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer) obteined not ſo muche at Goddes hand, as a droppe of water, becauſe he had defiled afore a crome of bread. We haue here a liuely example, what thei ſhall finde hereafter, that now in this<pb facs="tcp:150659:37"/>life doeth not prepare for theimſelfes frendes of the wicked Mammon, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſhalbe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their goodes whiche thei co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt their frendes, and be very beggers in deede, &amp; haue greate nede, thei ſhall find as this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> found, euerlaſtyng lackyng, &amp; euermore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng. There is no begger in worſe caſe, and a more miſer, then he that euer beggeth, and neuer obteineth. Suche ſhalbe all that dooeth as this man did. Therfore here in tyme what remedy Chriſt hath found, for as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as doth beleue him, and folowe his counſaill. Luke .xvi. I ſaie vnto you, (ſaith he) make you frendes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon, that when ye ſhall haue nede, thei maie receiue you into euerlaſtyng habitacions. Wil ye folowe Chriſtes counſail? while ye be here riche, and be able to make fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des by your riches, make them I counſail you. Geue here, and it ſhalbee geuen vnto you there, helpe the poore here, and thei ſhal help you there. Receiue theim here, and thei ſhall receiue you there. Loke what ye do vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here.<pb facs="tcp:150659:37"/>ſhalbe doen vnto you again there, bee it good or euill: for Chriſte compteth altogether, that is doen to one of his, beyng neuer ſo poore, to be doen vnto himſelf. And wher it is promiſed that thei (to whom ye are beneficiall here) ſhall receiue you into euerlaſtyng ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitacions: By that wee gather, that Chriſt of his goodnes, hath geuen the bothe goodes and aucthoritie, to dooe you good again, that haue doen theim good here. Here ye ſe, how to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, and how to bee abiected. Be good therfore vnto the poore, and do to them, as ye would that thei here after, ſhall do vnto you. And ſo ye do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng good vnto theim, ſhall dooe your ſelf greate good, and laie vp threaſure for your ſelfes, that neuer ſhall faile you. And ſo dooyng here, ye ſhall not lacke ther. And to the text again. And beyng in hell in tormentes, he lifte vp his iyes, &amp; ſaw Abraham a farre of, &amp;c. Here are in this parable that Chriſt propouneth, many ſtraunge thynges, to them that knoweth not the nature of a Parable. In a Parable, there be<pb facs="tcp:150659:38"/>many thynges feigned to be, that wer neuer doen: &amp; yet maie there be muche and Godly doctrine taught by theim. This one thyng emong many, is to be marked in euery Parable: the ſcopt, the meanyng and thend, wherfore the parable is ſpoken, &amp; all thynges in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, muſt be directed to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purpoſe. Now in this Parable ye muſte marke well, although here in the Parable, it ſemeth that thei that be in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or in a place of ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould bothe ſe and talke with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in the place of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation, yet there is no ſuche thinges in deede, but we muſte marke to what end chriſt ſpake this parable. He ſpake it to the Iues &amp; in them to all vs, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng bothe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vs, how to liue in this world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may liue in the world that is to come alſo. Here is in this Parable taught, how that wee maye not iudge, after the iudgement of the worlde, but after the Iudgement of God: whiche is knowen onely in holy ſcriptures, neither of thynges preſent in this worlde, neither of thynges in the worlde to come. Now once again<pb facs="tcp:150659:38"/>to the text: and beyng in hel in torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, he lift vp his iyes, and ſawe Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham &amp;c. Here muſt ye note (as I haue partly told you before) that although that Chriſt ſetteth furth in this para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as though ſoules departed out of this worlde, ſome to the place of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſome to the place of miſerie: ſhould ſpeake or talke one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet there is no ſuche thyng, nor Chriſt meaneth no ſuche thyng. But Chriſtes meanyng is, to teach vs that bee his, and here a liue, to bee ware of ſuche imaginacious or ſaiynges, as this man beyng in hell, doth ſaie here. For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Chriſt feigneth this man, to ſpeake in hell: euen ſo doth deuiliſh men imagin and ſpeake in yearth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſyng ſuche thynges to bee true, as this man in hell doth ſpeake, or is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Chriſt feigned to ſpeake. And ye muſte note alſo, that like as in this mannes ſpeakyng is ſignified all euill meſtnes imaginacions and ſaiynges: ſo here is alſo to bee marked in Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams ſaiynges, Gods will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure knowen in ſcriptures, for Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham<pb facs="tcp:150659:39"/>doeth ſpeake here in the perſone of god, and there is here nothyng ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of hym, but that is true, and doth confute all this wicked mannes aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; ſaiynges. Now let vs example the text, whiche ſaith: he beyng in hell in tormentes, lift vp his iyes, and ſaw Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a farre of, and Lazarus in his boſome, and he cried and ſaied, father Abraham haue mercie on me, and ſend Lazarus that he maie dippe the tippe of his finger in water, and coole my tongue, for I am tormented in this flambe. Now here is ſhewed the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginacions of them, that bee in helle in pain. Thei doo conſider the ſtate that thei be in, in helle, that is in pain and miſery. Thei do alſo conſider the ſtate of them that be in glorie and felicitie, and that doth augment their pain and miſerie. Thei beyng thus altogether wrapped in ſorow on euery ſide, ſhew their affeccion, &amp; deſiryng relief of the ſame, crie to Abraham (that repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth God) for mercie, but altogether is in vain, becauſe thei do it all out of due tyme. But Abraham ſaied: ſonne,<pb facs="tcp:150659:39"/>remember that thou in thy life tyme, receiue doſt thy pleaſure, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary-wiſe, Lazarus receiued pain, but now is he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, and thou art puniſhed. Here ſpeaketh almightie God in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams perſon, not onely to this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but rather to all menne, that doeth as this manne did. He aſketh mercie, but out of tyme. He would haue helpe of Lazarus, whom when he might haue holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he would not help. Therfore he heareth Abraham ſpeakyng the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of god to hym, ſaiyng: ſonne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre that thou in thy life. &amp;c. God doth call men to a reare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, becauſe thei do folowe their awne ſenſualitie, takyng in al thinges their awne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, thei regard nothyng at all what is gods pleaſure. Thei care not what God would haue theim dooe, but thei regard and onely care for their awne pleaſures, and ſuche thynges as thei will, and haue pleaſure to do. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alſo, that he calleth Abraham fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; alſo Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calleth him ſonne. But likewiſe as this man here beyng a liue and in proſperitie, regarded not<pb facs="tcp:150659:40"/>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to ſay god, any thing at al, &amp; he toke him not once for his father (except it wer with the mouth onely.) He loked for no helpe at his hande, he truſted not in hym, nor was for thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges receiued, thankful vnto him
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo doth Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to ſay god, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth hym ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne after the ſame faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as he called him father, nothyng meanyg to ſhewe his fatherly pitie, &amp; compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon hym, neither doeth he make hym once partaker of any parte of his euheritaunce; but ſaieth: Sonne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre that thou in thy life tyme, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuedſt thy pleaſure, &amp; contrarywiſe Lazarus receiued pain. As though he might ſaie, like as thou in the worlde, beeyng in high proſperitie, forgotteſt me, regardedſt me not, haddeſt no truſt in me to do thee good in time to come, but folowedſt thyne awne pleaſure; &amp; not myne, thyne awne will, and not myne, and was alſo in al thynges vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull. Remembre now how thou haſt doen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and therefore now thou muſt be concent to receiue there after Thou regardedſt not, neither my wil
<pb facs="tcp:150659:40"/>nor pleaſure then, but thyne awne: therefore now thou haſt, accordyng to thyne awne deſeruynges. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wiſe Lazarus beyng in aduerſitie, forgat me not, all tymes he regarded my waies. He put his whole truſte in me, to do hym good, in tyme to come. He folowed not his awne pleaſure, but myne, he did not his awne will, but myne. He was pacient in his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, and gaue thankes in all his miſery. Therfore, now is he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, and thou art now puniſhed. This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is not ſet furthe here, neither for this riche manne, nor yet for this poore manne, for thei can neither take good nor harme by it. But it is ſette furth (as all other ſcripture is) for vs to do vs good, to teache vs, to moniſh vs, whether we bee riche or poore, to haue before oure tyes, here in this worlde, whether we be in proſperitie, or aduerſitie, al tymes the ſtate of the worlde that is to come. If that wee would earneſty and often do this, we (I ſaie) of what ſtate ſoeuer we bee, truely, truely, it would make vs, that
<pb facs="tcp:150659:41"/>be riche to conſider, from whence our goodes come, to what purpoſe. God either did lende them vs, or put theim into our handes, it would make vs to remember what good, we beyng here riche, maie dooe vnto oure ſelfes in another worlde, (hourdyng vp oure Threaſure there) in miniſteryng the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame goodes, gladly, liberally, and with a louyng harte, to our poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and ſiſterne, accordyng to their neceſſitie, and our abilitie. It would alſo make vs thankefull to GOD, whiche hath geuen vs the ſame good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and hath made vs to be in a more bleſſed ſtate, whiche is in the ſtate of geuyng, accordyng to the ſaiyng of our Lorde Chriſte, in the Actes of the Apoſtles the twentie Chapiter, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſaieth: It is more bleſſed to geue, then to receiue. This doctrine alſo would make theim that bee poore and in miſerie, to bee pacient, and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to GOD their father, knowyng that ther is nothyng that can come or chaunce to theim, no, not one here<pb facs="tcp:150659:41"/>of their heade ſhall periſſhe, without either their fathers wil or permiſſion. Now therfore both riche &amp; poore take hede to this doctrine, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what is ſetforth in the ſame, either to eſchue of folowe. If ye take hede in tyme and folow this poore mans doyng, that is, the wyll &amp; pleaſure of god, walkynge trulie in your vocation, trulie ſeruing your callyng, doing in all poyntes to your power your duty &amp; office, bothe towardes God &amp; your neighbours, ye ſhall haue as this poore man (your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and examplar, doinge his office and ſeruing his vocacion) hadde, that is euen heuen for his labour. If ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not this doctrine ſetforth here in this parable of this riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but be negligent and careleſſe in doyng your office, and ſeruing your vocacion, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your ſelues to your owne luſtes &amp; pleaſures, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did, that that is written here in the parable to come to hym, doubtles ſhall come to you, that is to be perpetually damned in hel. It foloweth furthermore i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the texte: Beyond all this, betwene vs &amp;<pb facs="tcp:150659:42"/>you, ther is a greate ſpace ſet, ſo that they which wolde go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nce to you cannot, neither may come from thence to vs. Here is a nother doctrine of the heauenly father taught here by our ſaluiour Chriſt, in the perſon of Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham. By this doctrine of Chriſte here ſet furth, is ſignified vnto all men, that in a nother worlde, ther is no chaunge of thinges, but al thinges be ther firme, ſtable, ſuer and perpetual. Therfore they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ones made happy in that world (as all thoſe ſhalbe that doth departe in faith) ſhall for euer &amp; perpetually, remaine happy and neuer be chaunged, as Iohn ſaieth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>calipſe the .xiiii. Bleſſed are all they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> die in the lorde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of Ieſu Chriſte. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo they, that are once vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>happy, ſhal euer &amp; perpetually be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, &amp; ther is no place lefte of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng amendyng &amp; obteinyng of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Marke what is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes the .ij. chapiter. If the tree fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, ether to the ſowth or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> northe, in whatſoeuer place it falleth, ther it lieth. This doctrine is not ment of<pb facs="tcp:150659:42"/>fallyng of trees, but of the deathe of men. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> South is vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de faith, by the North infidelite. Lyke as the tree lieth ſtill where it falleth: So dothe the man ſignified ther by, abide ſtil for euer in one ſtate &amp; neuer chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth. If he die in faith he is ſaued, if in infidelitie, he is damned. So that he that is ones damned ſhall neuer be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, Euen ſo nomore ſhall he that is ones ſaued, euer after be dampned. Wher is then become purgatory, that hath put ſo many both great &amp; ſmal in a wanne hope, to be ſaued by other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s merites after their death? I truſt it be runne home again to his firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenter &amp; founder the pope. I wolde wiſh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al purgatorie mainteiners were with him alſo vntil I wold wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here again. Seyng that euery man at his death is either ſaued or dampned, wherfore is all that money beſtowed for the dead. If they be in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ther can no money increace ther ioy ther. If thei be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hel, ther can no money mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their paines there. Therfore the money that is beſtowed for the dead<pb facs="tcp:150659:43"/>with that opinion, either to increaſe the ioy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one, or to releſe the paine of the other, is euel ſpent. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead be neuer the better, and the liuyng beſtowers be moche the worſe. Why ſir may not a man geue his goodes to be beſtowed among the poore when he is dead? I ſay not nay. For ther is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell enowgh geuen vnto the poore by mens liues. Therfor I thinke it mete to geue at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſtwyſe at ther deathes. But I will counſel noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tary and differ is almoſſe vntill he die: for then I doubte whether it be his almoſſe or not. Or whether other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil geue for him that he coulde not finde in his owne harte to geue for himſelfe. We be bounde to geue that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be able to ſpare to them that hathe preſent neade and neceſſite, and not to tarie vntill we die, for then we geue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we can no longer kepe it, and I am a fraied that god ſhall thanke vs therafter, that is to ſay, nothyng at all. For he neuer gaue vs his goodes nor yet lent them vs to kepe them tyll we die, but in all our life tyme to<pb facs="tcp:150659:43"/>beſtowe them vppon the neady: &amp; not to kepe them that other men may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them for vs, or rather ſtriue for them after our deathe. Here we may lerne of this doctrine, that although this riche man begged a pace, (beyng in hell in tormentes), to haue bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſed of ſome of his paine: yeat he fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde no relief at gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des at al, for he aſked it to late. Nomore ſhall we finde at gods handes, if we come to late as he did, which died i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infidelitie. And as many as dieth in infidelitie, ſhall neuer obteine mercy, pray they neuer ſomoche for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, as this man is made mencion to do. And mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer and if all the whole worlde to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether wolde pray for one of them: yet ſhulde he neuer obteine any relief of his paine. Now by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, ther is nothing behind then but this, that both this riche man and his lyke companions muſt content them ſelues with ther ſtate &amp; paine that thei be in, &amp; neuer to loke for better. Now here we may ſee &amp; lerne by this doctrine of this place, that ther be nomore but ij.<pb facs="tcp:150659:44"/>places prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of this world, One for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are bleſſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a place of refreſhyng Another for them that are dampned, that is a place of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting. We finde not one worde in ſcriptures of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged purgatory, wherin ſowles be not purged, but fooles purſes be emptied.</p>
               <trailer>Here endeth the fowerth parte of this Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <p>BUt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this afore named riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaw y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could not preuaile any thing at al for himſelfe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he began to make his peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for other ſaieng: I pray the therfor father ſende him to my fathers howſe, for I haue fyue bretherne, for to warne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſte they alſo come to this place of tormentes. Here is alſo to be marked, in this parte of the parable, a nother damnable opinion ſpoken by this man being in hell, to teache them that are yet here in the earth, to be ware of it and ſuche lyke. This mans opinion was, as Chriſte teacheth here in the parable, that men wolde geue more credence to Spirites that come from<pb facs="tcp:150659:44"/>a nother worlde, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the holie ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures beyng taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here in thys world. This opinion is confuted here by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie Fathers doctrine taught by Chriſte in the perſon of Abraham, as ye ſhall heare hereafter This opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is confuted here of Chriſte, not for this riche mans ſake, nor for to teache hym and to conuerte hym, but it is ſet here to teache vs, to conuerte vs, whiche be yet here, where we may be taught, where we may be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Why? be there any nowe a lyue thinke ye, that be of that opinion that this riche dampned man was of? Ye trulie, I fere me to many. There be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be not aſhamed to vtter ther dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opinion, with theſe and ſuche lyke wordes: We knowe (ſay they) what we haue here, but we know not what we ſhall haue ther. Who dothe know, whether there be any other life after this life? Who wil chaunge (that wiſe is) the certentie of thinges that we be ſuer of here in this worlde, for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certentie of thynges that be to come,<pb facs="tcp:150659:45"/>in a nother (to vs vnkowen) worlde. Ther is none (ſay they) that will do thus except a few of momiſhe mopers whiche can do none other thyng elſe, but mope vppon ther bookes, to make vs afraied of ſhadowes and bugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beres. Therfore (ſay theſe wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) we wyll abyde in this our opinion, vntill we haue ſome meſſenger ſent from heuen or hell, to ſhew vs what newes be ther, and take our pleaſure here in the meane ſeaſon, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teche what they wyll. Of this opinion the parable teacheth vs that this riche man was, and he doth here repreſent all thoſe that be now of that opinion, and that anſwere that was made vnto hym than, is to warne them that be of ſuche opinion now. That the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doeth teach, this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be careful for his bretherne, that wer yet of the opinion that he was of: is not ſet here to teche that the ſowles in hell dothe care for them that are in earthe, but it is ſet here to teache vs to be carefull for our owne ſelues and for our fryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des alſo here, while care wil help. For<pb facs="tcp:150659:45"/>lyke as this mans care (that the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpeaketh of) preuailed not, nomore ſhall no mans care preuaile, nether for himſelfe, nor yet for other, that is not taken in tyme. What was this mans care in hell? that his bretherne all together vntawght of the will of god, that is, that they that lyue here in this world godly, folowing the wil and the pleaſure of god, ſhulde haue with god euerlaſting glorie, as he ſaw Lazarus had. And the contrarie wiſe, as many as toke ther owne pleaſure, regarding not the will of god, ſhulde be in paine euerlaſting, as he himſelfe was. This was his care, but to late. He ſaide, <hi>Vt teſtificetur illis,</hi> for to warne them (quod he) leſte thei alſo come in to this place of torment. This mans opinion thus farre was good, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde haue his bretherne warned, to be ware here i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lyfe furth But in this his opinion was nought, that he wolde haue one to come owe of a nother worlde to teache them, for that is a falſe opinion confuted here by our ſaluiour Chriſt, let vs be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<pb facs="tcp:150659:46"/>here in tyme, while lyfe is in vs. But let vs loke neither for Angell, ſowle, nor deuel to teach vs, but onely Scripture, as ye be here taught by Abraham ſpeaking in gods perſon to this riche man, and not onely to hym, but rather vnto vs, that we heringe this his doctrine, beleuing &amp; working after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, may be ſaufe: wher doing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie we ſhulde be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. For to warne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaieth the texte: To warne them of that (as though he might ſay) that I now finde by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that is, that vertue ſhalbe of god rewarded &amp; vice puniſhed. Of this let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, leſt perchaunce, they differre (the amendement of ther liues,) til they be dead, as I dyd, and then it wilbe to late for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be warned, as it is now to late for me.
<hi>Vt teſtificetur illis,</hi> for to warne them, &amp;c. By theſe wordes here he bewraieth his owne wicked opinion, that he had here whan he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. May not a man gather owt of theſe his wordes, this to be his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? I (as though he might ſay) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was yet a lyue. I iudged all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges<pb facs="tcp:150659:46"/>to be put vaine, whatſoeuer was ſpoken of the fire of hell, and of the puniſhmentes of malefactours in a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worlde. I ſuppoſed ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to haue bene but preachers drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to terrifie the ſimple people and ſelie ſowles, to kepe them in awe. Therfore I pray the good father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham to ſend Lazarus to warne my fiue bretherne and to teſtifie vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuerly not onely thoſe thynges to be moſt true, whiche holie ſcripture doth teache of the euerlaſtyng damnacion, whiche nether they nor I dyd beleue ones to be true, or any ſuche thyng to be in dede. Whiche thynges nowe, I am not onely compelled to beleue, but with myne owne hurte I fele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be to trewe, and to be ſuche paines as nomans tong can expreſſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nowe they that wyll not beleue ſuche thynges as the ſcriptures tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to be, with ther owne miſcheue and euerlaſtynge deſtruccion ſhall lerne by ouermuch experience (as this riche man did) ſuche thynges to be. Here ye haue harde this wicked mans<pb facs="tcp:150659:47"/>peticion for his bretherne, with his wicked opinion, that one owt of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worlde ſhoulde be ſent to teache them, but his peticion was not harde becauſe his opinion was wicked, and alſo he praied owt of tyme. To this wicked opinion, whether it be of this wicked man in hell (as the parable teacheth) or of ſuch like wicked men in earth, our ſaluiour Chriſte with the doctrine of his father ſpoken by Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, do make anſwere in this wiſe ſayng: They haue moſes and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, let them heare them. What is vnderſtande by Moſes and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes? By Moſes is vnderſtande Moſes doctrine, and by the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes is vnderſtande the prophetes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp; both thoſe doctrines taught that Chriſte ſhulde come, promiſed of god to do all thinges that belonge to our whole ſaluacion, iuſtificacion, &amp; redempcion. And that we by him onely ſhoulde haue remiſſion of our ſinnes and lyfe euerlaſting. Al theſe thynges we may and owght to learne by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the prophetes, that is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:150659:47"/>ſcriptures. Is there nothing elles to be learned but holie ſcriptures? No truelie, Nothyng that ſhall make any thinge for owr ſaluacion, iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion, redempcion, remiſſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and obteining of euerlaſting lyfe. Therfor we be taught here with theſe wordes: They haue Moyſes and the prophetes: let them heare them that is, let them geue eare to them, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regarde them, herken to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He ſaith not they haue with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reaſon, witte and wordly prudence: let them heart and hearken to them, let them folowe them. He ſaith not here, they haue Scribes and phariſeis, Fathers Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, long vſages, Many hundrede yeares, Mans tradicions, decrees and inuencions, Mens good intentes and meaninges, Multitudes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Doctours &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles and ſuch lyke, heare them: but he ſaith, that they haue Moyſes and the prophetes (that is holie ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res) let them heare them. For all theſe afore named thinges with ſuch lyke, put on one heape without ſcriptures<pb facs="tcp:150659:48"/>be of none authorite, but holie Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture without all theſe, is of full and perfect authorite. Therfore if we will be ſaued, let vs heare Moſes and the prophetes, that is holie Scriptures. Our ſaluiour Chriſte ſayed vnto the Iues, in Iohns goſpel the .v. chapiter Searche ſcriptures, for in them ye thinke ye haue eternall lyfe, and they are they whiche teſtifie of me. Alſo in Mathews goſpel the .xxij. chapitre our ſaluiour ſayed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saduceis: Ye do erre, not knowing the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. Here ye ſe all knowlege co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the knowing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, &amp; all ignoraunce alſo cometh for lacke of knowyng the ſcriptures. For they that knowe not the Scriptures that they are the worde of God, care for no godly thynge, thei take their pleaſure in al thing. Now the lorde that wolde haue al thyng done after a right order, that is by his owne rule, which is the holie ſcripture, ſendeth theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; alſo vs vnto the ſame ſcriptures: ſaieng. They haue Moſes &amp; the prophetes, let them heare them, obey them, kepe
<pb facs="tcp:150659:48"/>and obſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. How ſhal we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande this ſaieng of this place. They haue Moſes &amp; the prophetes: meaning this riche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fiue bretherne whiche know nothing leſſe then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. By this is ſignified nothing elſe, but that ther is none other lernyng to be ſaued by, then by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let euery man learne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> intendeth to be ſaued by this doctrine of Chriſte to knowe the ſcriptures, to teache the ſcriptures, to credite the ſcriptures, &amp; to leade a lyfe according to the ſame. And if this riche man had done this, he had not bene nowe in hell, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wolde neither heare it, nor haue it, neither read it, nor yet regard it, neither credit it, nor yet leade hys life after it, to conclude, he ſought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but refuſed al thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made for hys ſaltration, therfore muſte he nedes be dampned, &amp; ſo ſhall all that ſoo doeth. Now after that this damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned riche man had harde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of god (ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) infallibly true &amp; to be receiued of al men: They haue Moſes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes: Yet he was not<pb facs="tcp:150659:49"/>contented with the anſwere, but he replied againſt this manifeſt and open true doctrine and ſayed: Nay father Abraham, but if one come vnto them from the dead, they will repent. He ſayth vnto hym, if they heare not Moyſes and the prophetes, neither wil they beleue, though one roſe from death againe. Here ye may marke by this damned riche mans replication, the wicked opinion of them, that folow ther owne ſenſual iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and not goddes iudgement expreſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſette furthe by ſcriptures. For they ſay Nay, when God ſaieth yea, God ſaieth, they haue Moſes, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes to teache them, and them only muſt they heare, obey and folowe, for in theym onely is conteined enoughe and abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oauntly, al maner of doctrine that can, or maie helpe vs vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Nay ſay they, as this dampned man ſaid. Nay father Abraham (quod he,) not ſo, but if any man come vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the dead they wil repent. Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (as his damnable opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if ſuch one as Lazarus was that ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:150659:49"/>come out of an other worlde, raiſed vp againe from death to life, ſhould haue more credite geuen vnto hym, and men ſhoulde ſoner repent at his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng, then of either readyng, or preachyng of the ſcripture. But vnto that vaine and wicked opinion, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham (in goddes perſone) aunſwereth ſaiyng: If they heare not Moſes, and the prophetes, neither wil thei beleue thoughe one roſe from deathe againe. As though Chriſt might ſay. If there bee anye man, that wil not heare the doctrine of Moſes &amp; the prophetes to repente and amende his life at theim, ſurely that manne will ſone cauil and finde a fault, if any man woulde ſaye that hee ware raiſed vp from among the dedde, to bring any other new ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp; preceptes out of another worlde to learne men to repent &amp; amende by. Therfore let al men come onlie to the holy ſcripture. For there is more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte to be geuen to that onelye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then to al mens doctrines, to all mennes rules, inuentions, tradicions cuſtomes, miracles &amp; all other imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions<pb facs="tcp:150659:50"/>of men. This is a plaine and infallible rule, that the holie ſcriptur is the only rule to iudge and liue righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tly by. Whiche doeth comprehende all that belongeth to godlineſſe and oure Saluation. And is onelie of hymſelfe autenticke &amp; of aucthoritie, and ſo is nothyng elles in the whole worlde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men but it onely. For to haue bleſſed ſowles ſent vnto vs from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to admoniſh and preache vnto vs, this ware but vaine, and falſe. We be ſent here of the lorde to the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. They haue (ſaith God,) Moſes and the prophetes. Let no man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (that is of God, and entendeth to bee ſaued,) ones looke for anye appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of either Prophete, or Apoſtle, Thei whileſt thei liued, (by thinſtinct and inocion of the ſpirit of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ached vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ware preſent, and wrote for theym that ware abſent, all thynges that are ſufficient to inſtruct bothe them and vs. Let vs loke vpon their preachinges, and writinges, and content our ſelues with the ſame. Let vs not aſke with this wicked &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<pb facs="tcp:150659:50"/>riche man, that either ſaintes, or ſoules out of an other world, ſhoulde come, or be ſent meſſengers vnto vs. For ther is no credite to be geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſpirites raiſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deade. That doth the hiſtorie of Samuel raiſed (or rather ſuppoſed to be raiſed) againe, which is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the .i. Re. or. Sam. the .xxviij. cha. teſtifye. Furthermore we haue a plain comaundement of the lorde, that we ſhal not ſeke no trueth at theym that bee deade, in the boke of Deute. the .xviii. cha. Let none be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde in the (ſaith the lord) that ſeketh the truthe of them that be deade. If we maie not ſeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth at their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, much leſſe we may ſeke our ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation at their doctrine. Here ye may perceiue howe greuouſly they ſinne, that doeth geue credite and beleue to the aunſweres of coniured Spirites. It is poſſible by Goddes permiſſion, to come to paſſe that ſpirites ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere &amp; geue anſwer to certeine inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. But to tel the trueth what they be in diede, theſe are euen verye mockinges and deceiptes of the deuel.
<pb facs="tcp:150659:51"/>Although Satan ſometyme will telle truth, lyke as he did what ſhold come to Saul, as it apereth in the afore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed hiſtorie .i. Sam
.xviii. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng, he doth whatſoeuer he doeth to beguile &amp; deceiue euen ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as credite, and beleue hym. Seing then that Sathan is a lier, &amp; alſo the verye father &amp; beginner of lieng, ther is no faith to be geuen vnto hym. Fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thermore there is no reuelation of Angels to be loked for, whiche ſholde teache vs the Goſpel, for either thoſe Angels ſhould preache the ſame Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that the Prophetes and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hath preached, and ſo it ware in vayne, or els they ſholde preache con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Then marke what Paul ſaith to the Galathiens in the firſt Chapi. If we (ſaith he) or an Angel from he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auen, ſhoulde preache vnto you an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goſpel, beſides, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to that ye haue receiued, curſſed be he. Here it is manifeſt, that there bee no dedde mens ſoules to bee hearde. Angelles bee not to bee looked for. Mannes wiſedome in thys caſe, is not to bee<pb facs="tcp:150659:51"/>regarded, but onelye Moſes and the prophetes. For this doctrine of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the prophetes, did Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache, euen aftre his reſurrection. For as Luke ſaith. Chapit .xxiiij. He did interpretate, or expounde Moſes and the Prophetes. Wherefore here it is plaine, that the aucthoritie of theym is ſo by Chriſt confirmed, that we mai heare, nor credite anye other, either doctours, or preachers, for our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Therfore the way of ſaluacion is true, whiche Moſes and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and after theym, the Apoſtles haue taught, and beſides that waye, there is none other to be ſought, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if it ware ſoughte, there is none other to bee founde. This is the waie that they taught, that we knowledge our ſinnes, and belieue, that for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake, to haue remiſſion of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And in thys faith lette vs walke in gods vocation. Al this ſhal come to paſſe if we beleue chriſtes ſaieng to be true whiche is: Thei haue Moſes &amp; the prophetes, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now on the other ſide, they that contemne<pb facs="tcp:150659:52"/>ſcriptures, or miniſhe the aucthoritie of ſcripturs, make lighte of theym, or diſpraiſe them: of ſuch men if they do not ſhortelye repente, and retourne, there is no manner of hope, that by anye other waye, theye maye be brought to the way of their ſaluation accordyng to the true ſaiyng of oure lorde, If they (ſaith he) heare not Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and the Prophetes, (that is holye ſcriptures, neither will, theye beleue thoughe one roſe from deathe againe. Therefore of Angelles, of deade mens ſoules, of al Spirites, whether theye come from hel, or heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, muſt be auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, abhorred, and eſchued onelye the law and the prophetes, receiued &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde. Yet if a man wil conſider the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicions of the fleſhe, and of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and conſider the Iudgementes of both, it ſhal teache him to beware of thone &amp; to folowe the other. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is, that the ſcriptures whiche are the worde of God, that is Moſes &amp; the prohetes are ſufficient for our ſaluation. The fleſh on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide ſeketh for ſaluacion not only<pb facs="tcp:150659:52"/>at the Scriptures, but at manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtraunge thynges alſo. It ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe the trueth, at the deade, it ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth credite to ſpirites, to miracles &amp; to all maner of thynges taught beſide ſcriptures. But they that be taughte of the holy Ghoſt, beleueth, or geueth credit to miracles, and ſignes, for the wordes ſake, and not to the worde for the Signes and miracles ſakes. But theie that beleue after the fleſſhes perſwations doth contrary. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it commethe to paſſe often tymes euen by the very iudgement of God, that they that deſire rather ſignes &amp; miracles, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true doctrines of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to be deceiued with falſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, &amp; lyeng ſignes, for noman ought to beleue the truethe for ſignes and miracles ſake, before hee beleueth the word of truth. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures ſaith not, thei haue ſignes and miracles let the beleue them. But it ſaith: Thei haue Moyſes, and the Prophetes, lette theym beleue and credite them.</p>
               <p>By theſe thynges wee maye mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, that apperynges of ſpirites which<pb facs="tcp:150659:53"/>doeth ſhewe, and alſo require manye thynges) can not bee of GOD, but doubtleſſe they be wicked Spirites, whiche by the fearefulle and terrible iudgemente of God, (for mennes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulnes) dothe deceiue, and bring manye to errour. Here wee maie wel perceiue, that the will of God is, that we ſhould not be taught, neither of one thing, nor of other (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng our ſaluacion) but only of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or elles God woulde neuer haue ſpoken thus by Abraham: They haue Moſes and the prophetes, lette theim heare theim.</p>
               <p>Now I beſeche the God of al veri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and truthe, to geue vs all Grace, only as wee be commaunded to heare to harken to, to credite and obeye the onely woorde of God, that is Moſes and he prophetes, whiche are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truethe, and to faſhione our whole liues after theſame worde to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, and to oure owne Soules ſaluation. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
               <pb facs="tcp:150659:53"/>
               <head>A Short ſumme of ſuche thinges as our ſauiour Chriſt doeth te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache and admoniſhe vs of, in this preſent Goſpel.</head>
               <p>Firſt is that we vſe wel the preſent gooddes of this worlde. Here wee bee taught alſo to be merciful to the pore in diſtributyng &amp; miniſtring to theym thoſe gods goodes lent vs for theſame purpoſe. Here we be taught morouer that if we be not thankful to God for thinges receiued at his hande, and be mercifull to our pore neighbors with theſame goodes, that then we ſhalbee vnmercifully handled with perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al tormentes in hel. Alſo we bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to learne of the holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, what pleaſure we may looke for at Goddes hande, if wee here, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey hym accordyng to his owne wyll ſet furth in ſcripture and none other where. And contrary wyſe wee maye learne what paine wee ſhalbe ſure to haue if we do otherwiſe. Yet more we may learne that it is vaine, foliſh, and vngodly to loke to be taughte rather of theym of an other Worlde, then of<pb facs="tcp:150659:54"/>the holy Scripture, whiche is left to teache vs inthis world. Laſt of al, we be taught that al good, godly, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary thinges for our ſaluacion, are taught and plainly ſet furthe in holye ſcripture. And if ther be any that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth otherwyſe beleue, or of theſame doeth doubt, he, or ſhe, (as yet) doethe lacke the ſpirite of God, whiche doth teche al truth, and ſuche one abidyng in that caſe ſhal neuer geue credite to Chriſt himſelfe, nor to Prophete, nor Apoſtle, nor yeat to all the Aungel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in heauen, if they ware al ſente to conuert him, much leſſe ſhal he, or ſhe beleue the dead, if thei wer ſent to tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che him. Here we mai gather of what auchoritie the holy ſcripture is. And that there is therein expreſſelye ſette furth, al that is for our ſoules health, and wealthe neceſſary, and of done o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng to be knowen, but of it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in ſo much that if we do not heare that ſcripture only, credite it only, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, and faſhion our whole life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it only, we ſhal neuer finde any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng, beyng in heauen, earth,<pb facs="tcp:150659:54"/>or hel, that we may be ſaued by</p>
               <p>Now the God of heaueu, which is the maker &amp; aucthor of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, geue vs al grace gladly to rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iueit purely to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it, faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to beare it away, and effectually to liue aftre theſame, to the glory of god and to all our Soules healthe. To the whiche God, with our ſauiour Chriſte, hys deare ſonne, and with the holie Ghoſt, bee al honour, laude praiſe, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, for euer and euer, worlde with out ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:150659:55"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Grafton, Printer to the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nges Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Anno poſt Chriſtum natum. 1552.</p>
            <p>Menſe Maio.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the the seven liberal arts</figDesc>
               <head>VERSVTVS CELAT SCIENTIAM PRO .12.
<list>
                     <item>LOG</item>
                     <item>GRAM</item>
                     <item>ASTRO</item>
                     <item>RETHOR</item>
                     <item>ARITHM</item>
                     <item>GE<hi rend="sup">O</hi>MET</item>
                     <item>MVSIC</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Grafton</figDesc>
               <head>SVSCIPITE INSITVM VERBVM IACO .I.</head>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
